serve
serve
Academia Sinica's dramatic speech
中央研究院之dramatic speech
Colleagues in this hospital, guests outside the hospital, hello everyone
這個院內的同仁 院外的來賓 大家好
This new year begins this year
今年這個新的一年開始
We are very happy to invite Professor Zhong Yuan from the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University
我們很高興請到這個台大化學系的某中原某教授
Come give this month's intellectual feast
來給這個這一月份的知識享業
A certain professor has known him for 46 years
某教授是認得了46年
In 1966, many people were still unborn
當年1966年 還有很多人都還沒出生
In 1966, we were freshmen in the Chemistry Department of National Taiwan University.
1966年的時候 我們一起是台大化學系的新生
train together for success
一起在成功裡受訓
At the same time we are classmates
同時我們就同學
We all went to America in 1971
1971年我們就都去美國
Get Washington University
拿到Washington University 華盛頓大學
Ph.D. in St. Louis
在聖路易斯的博士
Then after postdoctoral
然後在博士後以後
play me two years back to Taiwan
玩我兩年回來台灣
Started his teaching position in Taiwan in 1978
1978年在台灣開始他的教職
By now everyone knows
到現在大家都可以知道
He's been switching fields along the way
他一路來領域一直在轉換
been converting
一直在轉換
I didn't do experiments by hand before.
以前是不動手做實驗的
He started with theoretical statistics
他從理論統計歷學開始
Then do the energy conversion later
然後後來做能量的轉換
these experiments start experimenting with
的這些實驗開始做實驗
Then his field is very wide
然後他的領域很廣泛
we have all in this scene
我們在這個場頭都有
Structure of Liquid Water from Statistics
從統計歷學液體水的結構
mesoporous molecular plug
中孔進分子塞
and its application
及其應用
There is also Feijun Xiangchumei
還有非軍向處梅
nanomaterials
奈米材料
for biomedical applications
用於生物醫學上的應用
and biological conditions
以及生物情況
So his field started from the physical chemistry group of the early chemistry department
所以他的領域從早期的化學系的物化組
From the present inorganic group to the present chemical biochemical group
到現在的無機組到現在的化生組
he stayed
他都待過
Ask him to teach some organic words
再叫他教一點有機的話
He becomes the domain of all chemistry departments
他就變成所有化學系的領域都化了
I don't think it's a waste of his time
我想也不浪費他的時間
Then everyone applauds and welcomes this report.
那就大家鼓掌歡迎來做這個報告
Thank you Xumin for the introduction
謝謝序民形容的介紹
good night listeners
各位聽眾晚安
I wish you all a happy new year here
在這邊跟大家拜一個晚年
still during the new year
還在過年期間
I think a lot of people haven't really gotten into the working situation yet
我想很多人還沒有真的進入工作狀況
Well, when I entertained the Chinese New Year earlier, I was at home a few days ago.
那早點娛樂過年的時候都是前幾天在家裡面嘛
then come out to play
然後會出來玩嘛
Come out and play later, right?
後面就出來玩對不對
Then we are very happy to see so many friends here tonight
那我們這個很高興今天晚上看到這麼多朋友來這邊
this feast
這個饗宴
good food
菜也不錯
this
這個
This is actually a small piece of research I did
我做的研究裡面其實這是一小塊
but as a public speaker he is more popular
但是作為一個大眾演講他是比較受歡迎的
Well, I'm here too and I'm not going to give my personal speech.
那我也在這邊不打算講我個人的演講
Just to talk about some thoughts on this subject
就是講一些有關於這個題材的一些想法
Then these thoughts may be helpful to some young friends
那這些想法也許對一些年輕朋友有點幫助
maybe it's okay
也許沒有沒關係
at least see if there is any entertainment value
至少看看有沒有點娛樂價值
nano-bionic materials
奈米仿生材料
Let’s talk about bionics first, bionics means to imitate some mechanisms of living things
先講仿生,仿生這個意思就是模仿生物的一些的機制
and its related this material
以及它的相關的這個材料
Unavoidable means that I imitate from a very small degree
難免的話意思是說我從很微小的程度就開始模仿
Materials for human development are a long way off
人類發展材料是很長遠的事
From this period, the Iron Age, to the present IC, what are these?
從這個時期時代這個鐵器時代一直到現在的IC什麼這些都是
This development of a material
一隻材料的這個發展
The recent materials all emphasize being smart and smart
那最近的材料都講求要聰明要smart
Biology gives us a good reference point
生物呢給我們很好的一個參考點
In fact, the scientist or engineer first started teaching this method
其實這個科學家或工程師最早開始這個講法
This man is famous
這個人的話是很有名
I think it's doing this
我認為是做這個事
the ancestors of this matter
這個事情的老祖宗
ah
啊
this
這個
what is this
這個什麼
he said this
他說這個
it should be possible
是應該可以的
this
這個
you are point
你這是point的
you want to move forward
你要往前
This is point
這是point的啊
I'm going down now
我現在要往下啦
the second one
第二張啊
he didn't pay
他沒有付
first pay one
第一付一張
ok
ok
ah
啊
Da Vinci
大文西
If in the future this line
如果將來這一行
to have a greatest award
要設一個最偉大的獎
Shouldn't be a Nobel Prize
應該不是諾貝爾獎
Should be the Grand Vinci Award
應該是大文西獎
first want
最早想要
mimic creature
模仿生物
make a
做出一個
Deed built
契建的
We can say that the earliest bionic
我們可以說最早的仿生的
biomimetic design is
模仿生物設計是
this great this big Vinci
這個偉大的這個大文西
this is his manuscript
這個是他的手稿
he
他
in the box
在箱子
this is an aircraft
這是一個飛行器
flying is a human
飛行是人類的一個
this dream
這個夢想
I want to be human for the people
我想從人類為民
people just want to fly
人就想要飛
That
那
In China, old Taoists used to tie this rocket to a chair and sit on it
中國以前還有老道士把這個火箭綁在椅子上坐著上面
fly up
飛上去
then fell to death
然後摔死
Now you also watch some extreme sports
那現在你也看了一些極限運動
All want to satisfy this desire
都是想要滿足這種慾望
Da Vinci
達文西
he
他
At once
就
design a flying machine
設計一個飛行器
You can easily tell at a glance that he is imitating a bird
你很容易一看就知道說他是在模仿一隻鳥
the flight of the bird
這個鳥的飛行
Of course at that time it was a matter of motivation
當然那個時候是動力的問題
no source of power
沒有跑動力來源
He can't make a plane
他並沒有辦法做出一個飛機
Immediately following the human desire to fly is not
緊接著人類的飛行慾望並不是
First use this aircraft
首先用這個飛行器
da vinci's flying machine satisfies
達文西的飛行器滿足的
but this
而是這個
balloon
氣球
This is the first time a human has gone to space
這個是人類第一次升空
In this Paris in 1783
1783年在這個巴黎
Avenue of Xiangxiao
香笑的大道
very large audience
非常多的觀眾
The so-called big science at that time
那個時候的所謂大科學
is this science
是這種科學
and ticket
而且收門票的
No need to apply to Congress for this research grant
不必跟國會申請這個研究經費
I charge tickets
我收門票
received tickets
收來門票
You can earn money to support your own research
就賺了錢可以養自己的研究
At that time, one of the famous participants was Charlie
那個時候參加的一個很有名的就是查理
charlie is a physicist
查理是個物理學的
one thing he's famous for is
他有名的一件事情就是
Study the temperature at which this volume is proportional to
研究這個體積正比的溫度
absolute temperature
絕對溫度
But I'll mention it later
但是我等一下會提
He actually wasn't Charlie the first to go up into space.
他事實上第一個升空的不是查理
the first to lead to charlie with a relative's ascension
第一個用親戚的升空導致查理
this is the same year
這個也是同一年
1783 than he played
1783年比他玩
This hot air balloon went up and played for months
這個熱氣球升空玩了幾個月
At that time it was a ban
那個時候是個禁止
patients, so there are many ordinary people who are willing to pay to support scientific research
病人 所以有很多老百姓願意付錢來支持科學研究
it's okay
真是還好啦
clear balloon
清晰的氣球
this is carmontisi
這個是卡蒙蒂西
According to Camontisi this electrolyzed water yields clear research
根據卡蒙蒂西這個電解水產生清晰的研究
So that's all the best research of our time.
所以那都是當代最好的研究
It's a pity that the biological science research list was not so popular at that time
可惜那個時候生物科學研究單還沒有那麼熱門
At that time it was physical chemistry
那個時候是物理化學
Relatively speaking, hot air balloons are more lively
相對來講的話還是熱氣球比較熱鬧
Because you're filling a hot air balloon for an afternoon
因為你要灌一個熱氣球一個下午
Wait about half an afternoon.
大概等個半個下午就可以
Everyone can see it and go up
大家就可以看到就上去了
The clear ball needs to be electrolyzed for a month
清晰球要電解一個月
After one month of electrolysis, the balloon is still clear enough
電解一個月以後那個氣球還夠清晰
But what follows is still not a bionic story
不過接下來仍然不是仿生的故事
still a balloon
仍然是氣球
By the 19th century balloon travel actually became a romantic affair
到了19世紀氣球旅行事實上是變成是一個浪漫的事情
A lot of people are fine, spend money on a balloon
很多人沒事 花錢買個氣球
No, buy this ticket and get on the balloon
不是 買個這個票 坐上氣球
Go to this other trip to play
到這個另外一個趟去玩一下
In the 24th period, even develop this
到了24期的話 甚至發展這個
This big letter balloon that slaughtered 1,000 people
宰客1000人的這個很大的這個信氣球
It's this balloon that travels across the Atlantic Ocean
是跨越這個大西洋的這個氣球來旅行
this is the restaurant inside
這是裡面的餐廳
Can do more than 1000 people, very big
可以做1000多個人的 很大
Of course it was a big disaster in the end
當然最後是一個很大的災難
When this new insurance number lands
這個新增保號這個降落的時候
stormy then out to this telecommunications and then
暴風雨 然後出到這個電信 然後
sunny day
晴氣燒起來
If I think about it now, if I was appalled at the time
這個如今想起來的話 當初如果有駭氣的話
This balloon flight may have broken down less suddenly.
這個氣球飛行也許不那麼突然就斷掉了
It means to say one thing
這說明就是說一件事情
Something that doesn't necessarily regenerate is useful
不見得反生的東西就有用
At least in Da Vinci's time at that time, the beauty was different
至少在當時達文西那個時期漂亮不一樣
It's beautiful, from an engineering point of view.
非常漂亮 從工程的觀點來講
is a beautiful design
是一個很美的設計
but it doesn't use
但它並不使用
what you want to achieve you have other ways
你要達到的目的 你有別的辦法
so i'll start with this
所以我先開始講這個
that means not to say
就是說意思並不是說
Anyway, it can solve your current slight problem
反正是可以解決你目前稍有問題
But the problem with this flight
但是這個飛行的問題
Of course, it's back to peeing in the end.
當然最後還是回到尿
Airliner Boeing Design We Are Doing Now
我們現在做的客機波音器設計
this
這個
basically from a bird's house
基本上是從個鳥的房
It was Da Vinci's idea
就是達文西的這個想法
coming
過來了
But the nearest plane
不過最近的飛機
you noticed
你們注意到
There are many further floors
有進一步的很多房層
you didn't notice the current plane
你沒有注意到現在的飛機
The wings and tails of many airplanes are raised
很多飛機那個翅膀尾巴是翹起來的
It is imitated the wings of this eagle
它是模仿這個老鷹的翅膀
There is this cock to make the air flow
有這個翹起來是使得空氣的流動
Generates more stable airflow
產生的氣流比較穩定
fly more stable
飛得比較穩
I remember airplanes from decades ago not being like this
我記得幾十年前的飛機不是這樣的
Now there is an artificial intelligence
現在的就是有仿生理智
But this is imitation big
不過這個都是仿的大的
not what i'm talking about today
不是我今天要談的
But let's start with this to illustrate a
可是開始用這個來說明一個
Even imitating the effects that living things can achieve
甚至模仿生物可以達到的效果
One of the most important dreams of mankind
在人類的一個最重要的一個夢想
on the aircraft to complete
飛行器上面來完成
Next, let's take a look at what the biology itself has
接下來我們來看一下生物本身有哪些東西
are we worth noticing
是我們值得去注意
and then go a step further to imitate
然後進一步來模仿
These are some of the nanostructures in nature that I'll show you first
這些是我先給你看一些自然界的奈米結構
And now scientists will want to mimic its
然後現在科學家將想要來模仿它的
The first one is this butterfly wing
第一個是這個蝴蝶翅膀
the butterfly wings
這蝴蝶翅膀
it has colorful things
它有五彩繽紛各種的東西
this is a variety of colors
這是各樣的顏色
But it is not made of pigment
但是它不是由色素
Usually we make the color of a thing
平常我們做一個東西的顏色
I draw a watercolor
我畫一個水彩
This variety of colors is due to different pigments
這個各種顏色它是因為有不同的色素
direct this
直接這個
The absorption light pattern is different due to the
吸收光圖不同而產生
It's not that it has a so-called optical crystal structure
它不是它是有所謂光晶體式的結構
periodic structure
有周期性的結構
after the light shines on
光照在上面以後
produced this
產生的這個
an interference phenomenon
一種乾涉現象
produced
產生的
It's like a gas leak on the road
就好像是馬路上漏了汽油
a thin layer of gasoline you will see the color
一層薄薄的汽油你會看到彩色
Then the structure of
然後這個結構的
of
的
periodic size
周期性的大小
When changing it has
變化的時候它有
different colors
顏色不同
In this case
這樣的話
For a deep point its design is simple
對於一個深入點它的設計很簡單
It only needs to adjust the color slightly
它只要稍微調整這個顏色就不一樣
It's the same Motive
它是同一個Motive
continue with the same design
同一個設計做下去
no need to go
不需要去
produce many different
生產很多不一樣的
pigment
顏料
chemical production
化學生產
It's good energy we all know
是很好能量我們都知道
The energy of chemical functions is the same in living organisms
化學功能量在生物體也是同樣的
You have to do all kinds of different compounds
你要做各式各樣不同的compound
that is energy consuming
那是很耗能量
it doesn't need to be
它並不是需要這樣
Also of course the famous history
另外當然很有名的歷史
Many people have heard of this
很多人都聽過就是這個
this lotus
這個蓮花
The water drop on the lotus
蓮花上面的這個水滴
is easy to roll
是可以很容易滾動
it can use this to collect water
它可以利用這個來收集水
Then pour this droplet into a lotus midsole
然後把這個水滴倒到一個蓮花中底
Although it's not raining
雖然已經都不下雨
But it is carefully
但是它用毛細心
To have collected water droplets method
要已經收集水滴方法
method can collect this liquid
方法可以收集這個液體
There are many structures on this
這上面的結構是有很多
Almost Zhou Qixing
幾乎是周旗星
but don't need this
但是不需要這種
But many fine bumps
但是很多細緻的凸起物
The so-called lotus effect
而造成的所謂蓮花效應
Of course we'll make sense of it
我們當然會提它的道理
If you go a step further, now this is a goose
更深一步的話,現在這個是有鵝
For geese, its central structure can be designed
鵝的話,它的這個中心結構可以設計的
very detailed
非常這個很細緻
So that the goose can have different colors when its wings are closed and when they are opened
以至於它鵝在收起來翅膀跟張開的時候可以顏色不一樣
And because the wings can be adjusted as they move
而因為在這個翅膀運動的時候可以調整它
Let's talk about it
另外談一下粒
grains, just light
粒,剛剛是光
Organisms use this inescapable structure to control light
生物體利用這個難免的結構控制光
the control particle
這個控制粒
this spider silk
這個蜘蛛絲
Spider silk is very strong and tough
蜘蛛絲的話,它的強韌度是非常強的
very strong
非常強
You've all heard this
你們都聽過這個就是說
In terms of units
以單位式來講的話
Its strength is stronger than steel
它的強度是比鋼鐵還要強
In addition, special mention
另外也是要特別講說
It absorbs vibration energy very well
它吸收振動的能量也很厲害
It's the wind that blows
就是這個風吹的話
It doesn't say it's vibrating very hard
它不會說是振動非常厲害
just break
就斷掉
It absorbs vibrational energy
它能夠吸收振動能量
It is of course a single row structure
它裡面當然就是單排質的結構
The structure of single-row mass can be very strong
單排質的結構可以做到非常強烈
and elastic
而有彈性
is our man-made fiber
是我們人造的纖維
Said that it is not yet so good
說還不能夠達到這麼好的
we have strong
我們有很強的
Like the mud dragon is very strong
像泥龍的是很強的
But the flexibility is not as good as
但是彈性就比不上
absorb this vibrational energy
吸收這個振動能量
not as good as
就比不上
Another letter
另外持信
This is a marine oil creature
這是一個海底油生物
I am not a student of biology
我不是學生物
I don't know much either
我也不太知道
what is its chinese name
它中文名字叫什麼
It has a row of tiny magnets inside its creature
它生物裡面有一排小磁鐵
This is raising Huashan iron
這個是飼養花山鐵
it can
它可以
and line it up
而且給它排好
This is for relative geology
這個對相對地質的話
sense of direction
它就方向感
it sense of direction
它方向感
The place it needs to live is in the water
它需要活的地方是水裡面
This place where the concentration of breeding is relatively high
這個養的濃度比較高的地方
The geological nature of that layer
那一層的話它的地質性
very different
特別不一樣
It can use this as a sensor
它可以用這個做一個sensor
If you add an additional layer
你如果外加一個層
If you hold a magnet against it
拿個磁鐵對著它的話
it will line up against this magnet
它就會對著這個磁鐵排一下
This it can control the magnetism
這個它可以控制磁性
we are in the lab
我們在實驗室裡面
little baffling little events like this
像這樣的小的難迷的小事件
easy to make
很容易可以做出來
Recent experiments in our laboratory
我們實驗室現在最近的實驗
development can not do
發展不可以做
but
但是呢
we can't make it yet
我們還沒辦法做出來
just let it line up
就讓它排成一排
and it's just that long
而且就這麼長而已
not too long
不要太長
just line up so long
就這麼長排成一排
we can't do it yet
我們還沒有辦法
So you can do a lot in this
所以這麼裡面可以做很多
And to achieve its special function
而達成它特別的功能
other words
另外的話
some of them
它們有些
We don't really know about this feature
這功能我們真的不知道
but it is very beautiful
但是就是非常漂亮
It's that simple
就這麼簡單
it can be done very beautifully
它可以做非常漂亮
This is the microalgae called plankton in the bottom of the sea
這是海底裡面浮游生物這個細藻
There are tens of thousands of species of algae
細藻有幾萬種
all the water in the world
全世界的這個水
Both freshwater and seawater have
淡水 海水裡面都有
it is a single celled organism
它是單細胞生物
Its main structure is the dioxide system
它的主要結構就是二氧化系
Another series of things it is calcium carbonate
另外一系列的東西它是碳酸鈣
all beautiful
都很漂亮
When the structure of this it is like that
當這個的結構它是像那個
The one in the Forbidden City
故宮的那個
What is that called Jiulongshu?
那個叫什麼九龍書
many layers
好多層次套的
all have holes
都是有孔洞
that's a typical
那這是一個典型的
In this case, its full gene has been solved
這個的話它的全基因已經解出來
know the structure of this gene
知道它的這個基因的結構
it looks like two pieces of that
它好像是兩塊那個
The pins are hooked together
那個針發命套在一起
There is a belt in the middle
中間有個腰帶
Different slender it's all beautiful
不同的細長它都很漂亮
but looks different
但長的樣子不一樣
You can classify it by its appearance
你可以用它的長相來做分類
Inside is a single cell
裡面就是一個單細胞
so
這樣
of course we know
我們當然知道
Its main function is to protect
它主要一個功能是來保護它
that is
就是說
It's hard, isn't it?
它硬的嘛 對不對
Then the hole can pass oxygen
然後洞可以通氧分
But we really don't know why it grows so beautiful
但我們實在不知道它幹嘛要長這麼漂亮
this is also
這也是
this
這個
confused one
迷惑之一
In addition
另外呢
in the lab
在實驗室裡面
draw a family today
今天畫一家
Dioxide systems can be easily made
可以很容易做出二氧化系
Porous carbon dioxide system can be made
可以做出有孔洞的二氧化系
but absolutely can't do it
但是絕對做不出來
we are far away from this
我們離這個很遠很遠
We can't make such a beautiful thing
我們做不出來這麼漂亮的一個東西
don't know how it's made
也不知道它是怎麼做出來
do not know either
也不知道
don't know
不太知道
know a little bit
知道一點點
this is a creature
這個是生物
some of some material
一些材料的一些
brief introduction
簡單的介紹
when you start
當你先開頭
Know that he can do many things
領略他可以做很多本領的
to meet the needs of his life
來達到他生活的需求
In addition
另外呢
We are all familiar with Google
我們大家最熟悉的就是谷歌
this
這個
There are many properties in biological materials that are
生物材料裡面有很多特性是
it
它
yes
是
not heart
不是使心的
it is hollow
它是空心的
Then what
然後呢
It has a so-called layered structure
它有所謂接層式的結構
this is not shown
這個沒有顯示出來
here
這邊
it doesn't matter
沒有關係
this
這個
Google puts Aratu in your stomach, you can see it
谷歌放肚子阿拉圖你可以看出來
it's light
它滿輕的
especially bird
尤其鳥的
very light bone
骨頭很輕
but
但是呢
It can support a strong force
它能夠支撐很強的力
this weight
這個重量
it's the most important thing
它最主要呢
there will be
會有
so-called layered results
所謂接層式的結果
Let me explain this first
這一點在這邊先說明
must use this opportunity to say
一定用這個機會來說
Explain what is a layered result
說明一下什麼是接層式的結果
behind us
我們後面
meeting
會
talked about
談到
It's a bone about a centimeter in size
它這是一個差不多公分級的一塊骨頭
and you start zooming out
然後你開始往下縮小
The seventh stage of the shrinking company has a unique structure in each size
縮小連的七級在各個尺寸都有獨特的結構
Let's start with the smallest skeleton, which is divided into two parts
我們先從最小的看起骨格它分成兩部分
Inorganic and Organic
無積物跟有積物
The non-deposit is basically this spiritual acid calcium
無積物基本上是這個靈酸鈣
Calcium Spiritate with Oxygen Clearing
有清氧跟的靈酸鈣
It's the little thing in the middle of the drawing here
是這邊畫起來的中間的這一塊小小的東西
And then another strong protein like muscle protein
然後另外是類似肌肉蛋白的很強的蛋白
called Collagen
叫 Collagen
it is arranged like this
它這樣排列
This is the word in the smallest size
這是在最小尺寸的話
There are probably tens of nanometers to several nanometers here
這裡大概有幾十個奈米到幾個奈米
Then
然後
Color Gyn stacks up here
Colour Gyn這邊都疊起來
Then discharge a structure in a very orderly manner
然後再很有次序的排出一個結構
This is the protein structure
這個是蛋白質的結構
is one of the so-called triple helixes
是所謂這個三螺旋的一個
Because of this triple helix it's a very strong protein
因為這個三螺旋它是一個很強的蛋白質
Then what
然後呢
further words
進一步的話
it forms this fiber
它形成這個纖維
This fiber has a gradation from small size to large size
這個纖維有階層從小的尺寸到大尺寸
to the fiber
到纖維的
That is where you put this small piece or this piece
就是你拿這一小塊放在哪裡還是這一塊
Immediately, where to put this small piece or this piece
馬上這這一小塊放在哪裡還是這一塊
Take this small piece where to put it or this piece
拿這一小塊放在哪裡還是這一塊
You keep looking this way until you get to the big size
你一直往這邊看就是到大尺寸
Go all the way here to the small size
一直往這邊到小尺寸
its different sizes
它不同的尺寸
To adjust and make such a complex structure
去調整做出這麼複雜的一個結構
We usually build, look at a building
我們平常建築 你看一個建築
Building a building like 101 is complicated enough
建築如果蓋一個101這樣的大樓是夠複雜了吧
but
但是
basically
基本上
If from the room to the floor to the whole building
如果從房間到層到整棟樓
just such a change
這樣的一個變化而已
and quite monotonous
而且相當單調
This is a very complex structure
這個是一個很複雜的結構
Of course we can't do it in the lab.
我們當然在實驗室也沒有辦法做出來
we don't know much
我們也不是很了解
The whole body of this bone
這個骨骼整個形成的這個
What is going on in the physical and chemical process
物理化學過程到底怎麼回事
Then let’s talk about why Nano
那接下來就談談說為什麼要Nano
Why Nano
為什麼Nano
From the few examples just mentioned
從剛剛講的幾個例子
you can tell
你可以看得出來
Nano is its bottom foundation
有Nano才是它的最底下的那個基礎
The bottom foundation builds up
最底下的基礎往上搭
build this
搭成這個
This hierarchical structure
這個階層式的結構
the bottom of this foundation
這個最底下的這個基礎
when going to ride out
去搭出來的時候
The thing at the bottom can be changed again
最底下那個東西還可以再變
It can be operated differently
它裡面可以不同的經營變
but not the same as above
但是不一樣上面的
It keeps this pretty consistent
它保留這個很一致
Many of our things are buildings
我們很多東西如果是建築物
If we build it like this
我們如果這樣建吧
I started pumping some bricks
我開始抽一些磚子
You can smoke a few bricks
你抽幾個磚頭還可以
You can't do it if you smoke too much
你抽多了就不行啊
those bricks are going to fall
那些磚頭要垮
but
但是呢
Its bricks can still change
它那些磚頭還可以變化
What about the second one?
第二個呢
it is autonomous brick
它是自主磚
not like we build a house
不像我們蓋一個房子
we have workers
我們是有工人
there are architects
有建築師
Architects are drawing blueprints to design good
建築師是畫出藍圖設計好
In the future, workers will build according to this blueprint
以後工人按照這個藍圖來建
so there is outside
所以是有外面的
these people come in and do this
這些人進來做這些
no problem
這問題沒有啊
it is to self-assemble
它是要自組裝
So it needs to start with nano cities
所以它需要從奈米城市開始
go up and assemble
去往上去組裝起來
there's no way you can get chunks of stuff
你沒有辦法大塊的東西
Will fly around and self-assemble
會飛來飛去自組裝
Only small enough things of course
當然只有夠小的東西
it has brownian motion
它有布朗運動
These Brownian motions go
這些布朗運動去
movement to assemble
運動去組裝
organic matter, inorganic matter
有機物、無機物
Single pendulum planting, carbonic acid cover what
單擺植、碳酸蓋什麼東西
it can do
它都可以去做
to assemble
組裝
In addition
另外呢
a physics student
一個物理學生
What everyone likes to talk about is the nature of the so-called world view
大家喜歡講的 是所謂的界觀的性質
at a mesoscale
就是在一個中尺度
When going from nanometers to the scales in between
從奈米到居觀中間的尺度的時候
it's different
它性質不一樣
Nami's heart
譬如說奈米的心
it's not golden
它就不是金黃色
it can be purple can be blue
它是可以是紫色 可以是藍色
when it was at that nanoscale
它在那個奈米尺度的時候
look different
看起來性質不一樣
when the organism goes
那當生物體去
When using this nanoscale to do things
利用這個奈米尺度做的事情的時候
It equals some more degrees of freedom
它等於多了一些自由度
It's not just 100 elements
它不只100個元素
it is equal to many other
它等於有很多其他的
Like the color of the butterfly wings I just mentioned
像我剛剛講的那個蝴蝶翅膀的顏色
it is made of the same material
它是用同一個材料去做
Then in the mesoscale the arrangement is not the same
然後在中尺度排列不一樣
its color can vary
它的顏色可以不一樣
So these are the things it needs to understand at the nanoscale
所以這些是它需要奈米尺度的了解
to understand the reasons for its results
去了解它的結果的原因
Then I can't go deep
那我沒有辦法深入進行
because that's what it is
因為這就是其實
Talking about what needs to be studied in depth
說研究裡面要深入的東西
I can't be in this person today
我沒有辦法在今天這個人裡面
just tell you
只告訴你
That is to say, what does this concatenated structure do?
就是說這個接成式的結構什麼做
In fact, in the butt that kind of thing
事實上在股頭那種東西
I can't make it
我也沒辦法搞成
because no one knows
因為沒人知道
But there are some things we can imitate to do these
但有些東西我們是可以模仿的做這些
we can't talk today
我們今天也沒有辦法做談
The next thing I'm going to talk about is saying
我緊接著要談的是說
we bionic words
我們仿生的話
what to do
要做什麼實現
Of course I can use examples one by one
我當然可以用一個一個例子來講
explain
說
Anyway, I can make a strong pull by doing this.
反正做這個我可以做很強拉力的
this elastic material
這個有彈性的材料
There are optical properties when we do it
做那個的話有光學性質
but i'm not going to talk
但是我不打算講
i'm going to ask a question
我打算提出一個問題
These questions are like Da Vinci's original
這些問題就像達文西當初
raised a human dream
提了一個人類的夢想
a big problem
一個很大的問題
In fact, after this big problem
其實這個大問題以後
let's see what's there
我們來看看有哪些東西
We can do it with bionic technology
我們可以用仿生的技術來做
This is perhaps an important contemporary question
這也許當代重要的問題
It's a matter of energy
就是能源的問題
right now we
我們現在
energy problem
能源有問題
I'm looking for new energy
我要找新的能源
And find the right energy and it needs to be green energy
而且找對性能源而且需要是綠色能源
What most of us know about green energy is
我們一般人對綠色能源來的了解就是
I don't want to burn that oil coal
我不要去燒那個石油煤
no nuclear energy
也不用核能
Then the rest is solar
然後剩下就是太陽能
or use this
或者是用這個
Solar energy produces that hydrogen in hydrogen generation
太陽能產生那個氫氣在氫氣作成
Combustion batteries and so on, these so-called green
燃燃電池等等這些所謂綠色
But I feel that everything is not green enough now
但我都覺得現在所有東西不夠綠
The original meaning was that you just agreed to say that I will not use these petrochemical energies.
原意是你只是達成說我不去用這些石化能量
But your design doesn't have any biological principles in it
但是你的設計並沒有任何生物的原理設計在裡面
so start talking about us
所以開始說我們
Now let's think about this
目前來我們來想這個問題
Just like when Darwin thought about how to fly
就像當初達文心想說怎麼飛這個問題
This is a big issue we face
這是我們面臨一個大課題
It may take decades for us to do this subject well.
這個課題要好好做的話也許我們需要幾十年
What I mean is to say it well, I really did it, and in the end it was really green
我所謂好好說我真的做到最後真的是很綠
is the highest efficiency
就是最高的效率
To achieve the economic efficiency that biology can achieve
達到生物能夠達到那樣的經濟的效率
Let's look at solar cells first
我們首先看太陽能電池
Solar cells I'm talking about solar chemical cells
太陽能電池我這邊講的是太陽能化學電池
not that one
不是那個那個
Originally made with this Xijing
用這個細菁原作的
that
那個
of course now
當然現在是
We usually buy it in foreign countries
我們一般你在外國去買
buy a solar panel
買一個太陽能的那個板
or something
或什麼的
Just use Siri
就是用Siri工
what we are saying now is
我們現在說的是
like attorney ye
像葉律師一樣的那樣
but it can be converted into chemical energy
但是他可以轉換成化學能
or converted into electrical energy
或者轉換成電能
then you have sunshine
那你有太陽光
sunlight coming in
太陽光進來
later you have
以後你有
booster here
推化器在這裡
Then you have the anode
然後你有陽極
then you have this
然後你有這個
cathode
陰極
anode for reaction
陽極進行反應
splits water into oxygen
是把水分解成氧
The reaction at the cathode produces hydrogen
陰極進行反應是產生氫
Then simultaneously generate current
然後同時產生電流
Of course you can adjust
你當然是可以調節
Can make this a little less current a little more
可以讓這個少一點電流多一點
No need to click a button, it will directly produce new oxygen
都不要點鈕 就直接產生新可氧
use it
拿來用
wait but this
等等 但是這個
One is from the sun
一種是從太陽能來的
Now of course many people are doing this problem
現在當然非常多人在做這個問題
Then maybe there are a lot of refugee designs in it
那也許其中就有很多難民的設計
like this is a refugee design
像這是一個難民的設計
this
這個
But let's think about something like this
但是讓我們思考這樣的問題
we need to control many things
我們需要控制很多事情
we need to control the light
我們需要控制光
We want to control the current
我們要控制電流
we want to control the gas
我們要控制氣體
it has gas coming out
它有氣體冒出來
or fuel electrons when I'm gas going in
或燃料電子時我是氣體進去
gas run
氣體跑
gas in and out
氣體進出
These organisms are
這些生物體都
all do this
都幹這個事的
you a fast running newspaper
你一個快速奔跑的報紙
It is a very large energy consumption
它是非常大的能量在消耗
it sucks in that
它吸進來那個
Oxygen instant air is a lot
氧氣瞬間空氣是很多
how does it manage
它怎麼樣去manage
why is that management
怎麼那是管理
This gas when it is divided into every body in its entirety
這個氣體當它分到它全部的每一個身體
every cell
每一個細胞
integrate it into the cell
把它集入細胞裡面去
fastest way
最快的方法
Can be labeled as a great power
能夠打成一個很大power
How to do
要怎麼做
In addition, the fuel cell
另外的話燃料電池
For example, what I just did
譬如說我剛剛做的東西
I made blue silver oxygen
我做成青銀氧
blue silver oxygen delivery
青銀氧輸送去
Then go to other drug areas to use wide
再到別的藥區用寬
Or do it by generating electricity
還是用產生電的方法來做的話
fuel cell
就所謂燃料電池
Here is a simple fuel cell schematic
這是一個簡單的燃料電池示意圖
It is to let green react with oxygen
是讓青跟氧反應
in two motors
在兩個電機
electrolyte in the middle
中間有電解質
Electrolyte is going straight
電解質的話是直直跑過去
Then this is of course very environmentally friendly
那這個當然是非常環保
because you are water
因為你就是產生水
you have no pollution
你沒有產生污染的東西
You didn't produce filth
你沒有產生污石細體
carbon dioxide
二氧化碳
Thanks
謝謝
OK
OK
This digging diagram is too simplified
這個挖的圖是太簡化
You are your student
你是你交給學生
The first time you give it to me, you will say this
第一次交給我 你是會這樣講
But that's what I just said about a newspaper going fast
但是就是我剛剛講一個報紙要跑得很快
It's definitely not that simple for the gas to come in
它這個氣體絕對進來不是那麼簡單的
Just to do an experiment in our high school
就是到一個我們高中做實驗
make a board
做一個板子
Blow it onto that board
吹到那個板子上就是
that doesn't have much power
那沒有多少力量的
Because the surface area is too small
因為表面積太小
another this
另外這個
Oxygen here is also oxygen
氧這邊也是氧
And what about this pointing
然後這個直指怎麼樣
Traditionally, these are the problems you have to manage
傳統這些都是你要manage的問題
Your problem with the flow of this object
你的這個物體流動的問題
if we put it
我們如果把它
If you take a closer look
撲開細一點來看的話
You need a lot of area here
你這邊需要大量的面積
What about this area?
這個面積呢
makes it easy for hydrogen to walk
使得氫氣很容易散步
like the lungs of a newspaper
就好像一個報紙的肺
you want to be able to walk to
你要很快能夠散步到
All Blowing Agents Above
所有的吹化劑上面
electrons are then produced
然後產生出來的電子
soon again on this conductor
很快又可以在這個導體上
to run
去跑
run out tell me to get out
跑出外點我出去
other side
另外這邊的
So, therefore, it's the oxygen side that does the reaction
因此,因此就是氧這頭,進行反應
Also like this
也是這樣
Another important point is to have a blowing agent
另外還有一個重點是要有一個吹化劑
Modern working blowers are generally made of platinum
現代的工作吹化劑普遍是用白金
Incredible Platinum Particles
難迷的白金顆粒
So in response to a Platinum conduction
所以在一個白金進行上的反應的話
When the time is generated, run from this electrolysis value to the opposite side
產生的時子從這個電解值跑過去要到對面
other electronic words
另外電子的話
Very close to a conductor
很靠近就要一個導電體
usually carbon
通常是用碳
porous carbon
多孔的碳
ok , you just imagine this one question
好啦,你就想像這個一個問題
like a living organism
像是一個生物體
You have to manage the gas and your liquid
你要manage這個氣體跟你的液體
How about the fastest exchange to flow
怎麼樣最快速的交換去流動
blown
然後產生的吹化
Here we immediately see one thing
在這裡的話,我們立刻看到一樣事情
We know that if we really want to make the electrons of the sun
我們知道真的要把太陽的電子做下去的話
Don't do that, it's platinum
不能這樣幹,就是白金
platinum is expensive
白金很貴的
And there are not many platinum reserves in the world
而且全世界白金的儲量沒有多少
Where are you going to make this electronic
你如果都哪來做這個電子
Probably only for one country, the United States
大概只能給一個國家用嘛 美國吧
no one else
其他人就沒有了
We obviously have to find other
我們顯然要找出其他的
Then we have to ask whether there is anything in the organism
那我們要問生物體裡面有沒有什麼東西
can do something like
可以做類似的事情
so this imitation
所以這個模仿呢
From the comparative physics of this fluid
從比較物理的這個流體
How to exchange gas and liquid
氣體 液體怎麼交換
We have a structure to catalyze
我們有的一個結構到催化
that in chemistry
那在化學的話
so-called biochemistry
就是所謂生物化學就所謂效屬
how do you tie this thing together
你怎麼樣把這東西都綁在一起
become an integrated organism
變成一個整合的有機體
then i pose this question
那我提出這個問題來
let's see what you're going to manage
讓我們來看你要去管理什麼東西
What kind of experience do you have in managing this process
在管理這個過程你有什麼樣的
biomimetic approach to do
仿生的方法來做到
efficient and cheap
高效率又便宜
Let's not wait for these with platinum
我們不要用白金等這些
I ask this question is now
我提出這個問題是現在
Cutting-edge research that everyone is doing
大家正在做的最尖端的研究
it's not me
也不是我在做
Instead, let's bring this up in exchange for this idea
而是說我們來提這個用這樣的想法來換
can there be some new ways
是不是可以有些新的路
Of course, this is to manage sunlight, air and water.
當然這個就是要管理陽光空氣水
Right, we just needed three things and that's it
對不對 我們剛剛需要三件事情就是這樣
I'm not advertising for the tourist bureau
我不是在幫那個觀光局做廣告
But what I'm going to illustrate using this instruction
但是我要說明的利用這個說明
It is how you manage sunlight, air and water
就是你怎麼樣去管理陽光空氣水
ok let's look at the first thing
好 讓我們看第一件事情
Sunshine is just this
陽光 就是剛剛這個
Right, the first thing is the light
對不對 第一件事情就是光
Now if you look at the current solar panels
現在你看注意到現在的太陽能板的話
will still shine
還是會發亮的
When it is replaced, there will be light reflection back, it is not used
換掉的時候就有光反射回來 沒有用到
It doesn't work. You better suck all the light in.
沒有用到 你最好所有光都吸進去嘛
right
對不對
And bacteria are useful
而且細菌都有用到
this is the biggest
這是最大
There is no principle of heat to tell you that some light must be reflected back
沒有什麼熱力的原理告訴你說一定要有些光反射回來
you just need
你就是要用到
common now
現在普遍
It doesn't matter if it's made of bacteria or glass
用的不管細菌也做或者玻璃做
Some of the light is reflected
都有一部分反光反射出去
that's wasted
那就已經浪費了
Organisms can be completely bacteria
生物體可以做到完全就細菌了
It's the perfunctory of the black forehead
就是黑額的敷衍
it is also a perfunctory
它也是個敷衍
that is, each one is
就是每一顆都是
Each of these is a cell
這裡面每一個都是細胞
And then a further fine-grained structure looks like this
然後更進一步細微結構是這樣
it's going to be all black
它要做成全黑的
what is the reason
原因是什麼
It only comes out in the middle of the night against time
它只有半夜出來逆時
night
晚上
words at night
晚上的話
shine a little light on you
你上發一點光
Others saw it and ate it
別人就看到了來吃它了
So it is completely non-reflective
所以它做到完全不反光
Let's look at this physics principle first
我們先看這個物理學原理
Principles of Physics
物理學原理
if i have two things
我如果有兩個東西
one glass one air
一個玻璃一個空氣
only one interface
就只有一個界面
two rings
兩個戒指
Then everyone has learned the light will go on
那大家都學過光會下去
then there will be a part
然後會有一部分
regardless of reflection
不分反射回來
It depends on the difference between the two dielectric coefficients.
就看這兩個界電系數差的大不大
If it's glass and air, there's a big difference.
如果是玻璃跟空氣那可差大了
The difference is very big because the air is very cellular
差的很大因為空氣很細胞
Boundary electrical coefficient is almost 1
界電系數幾乎是1
About 2.5 for glass
玻璃的話大概2.5吧
That's not the dielectric coefficient this refractive index
那不是界電系數這個折射率
But if you have a layer of coating in the middle
那但是你如果中間差近一層coating
The dielectric coefficient of this coating is between these two
這個coating界電系數介乎這兩個中間
You will reflect less at this time
你這個時候反射出來就少一點
it certainly looks like two chances
它當然看起來有兩次機會
But every time it comes out less
但是每一次出來就少
The best situation is infinite layers from here to here
那一個最好的狀況就是從這邊到這邊無限多層
something from the index of refraction of a glass
從一個玻璃的折射率的東西
Until the air changes continuously
一直到空氣是連續的變過去
That black forehead is done and that's it
那黑額就乾了就是這樣
it does this structure
它做的這個結構
You look like a protocone from the side
你從側面看是一個原錐的東西
Then periodically
然後周期性排列
Then you can see that there are fewer and fewer things that can be blamed.
那你看已經可以原罪的東西就上面越來越少
that is from
那就是從
Looking at it layer by layer
從這一層來看一層一層
Refractive index decreases from now on
從現在往上折射率就減少
In the end, all the light goes down without reflection
到最後就是所有光下去不反射
In this case
這樣的話
I think
我覺得
should be
應該就
is a do
是一個做
A good material for solar panels
太陽電池面板的一個好材料
The light that goes in doesn't come out
進去的光就不出來了
this black thing
這個黑的東西
of course
當然呢
people
人們
Noticed this early on and now figured out how to do this
很早注意到這些現在想辦法做這個
tie this
綁這個
but not for solar cells
但不是用來太陽電池
Solar cells are not so expensive now
現在太陽電池還沒那麼高貴的價錢
say in stealth plane
說在隱形飛機
stealth plane
隱形飛機
That electromagnetic wave owned by that stealth plane
那個隱形飛機所有的那個電池波
from that
從那個
microwaves to this visible light
微波到這個可見光
The entire spectrum is completely non-reflective
整個光譜全部都不反射
that's black
那就是黑的
then you can't see
那你就看不到
In fact, this research
這方面研究其實
Central Plains Institute is doing well
中原院做得很好
these two
這兩位
Because of Chen Guixian
因為陳貴賢
Because it was originally locked because Lin Yuxiong was too big and there were too many forests
因為原本鎖 因為林玉雄太大林太多
is next door to me he is actually next door
就是我的隔壁 他實際是在隔壁
so i know what they do
所以我知道他們做什麼
They specialize in doing a lot of one-dimensional
他們專門做很多一維的 原追的
I just said that he wants to follow the original type
就是我剛剛講他要原追型
Raw chai materials, you can see that they make all kinds of materials
原追的材料 你看他們做各式各樣的材料
This desalination plus fine arts, shower plus and so on these materials
這個淡化加 細藝啊 淋化加等等之類的這些材料
how to do it i'm not talking too much
怎麼做 我不是多講
I'm just talking about the application of the so-called plasma
我只是講說 適用所謂這個電漿
or plasma discharge
或者說等離子體 放電
Then release all kinds of temperament
然後放出 放各種各樣的氣質
Temperament needed If you want to do desalination
需要的氣質 如果說要做淡化系的話
You just put the thin bowl and this bowl down
你就放細碗跟這個夾碗下去
then excited in the plasma
然後在電漿激發
Break it down into molecules and start to grow
把它分解分子以後開始長上來
This is a device for microwave discharge of plasma
這是一個電漿的微波放電的一個設備
They made it in 2007
他們做出來的 在2007的時候
I haven't asked them lately
我最近沒有問他們
they should be
他們應該是
There is more progress and improvement
有更進步改善
will be to the whole world
將對於全世界就是
This is the original
這個是原本所的
this
這個
This is their original one
這個就是他們原來的一個
Silicon Wife
Silicon Wifre
Then after it grows this colorful coding
然後經過它長出這個彩的coding以後
is black
就是黑的
Then this reflective green word
那這個反射的綠的話
about percent
大概百分之
one percent
百分之一吧
maybe less than one percent
可能百分之一都不到
a few tenths of a percent
百分之零點幾
It's a very black thing
就很黑很黑的東西了
this is one
這個就是一個
imitate this black forehead
模仿這個黑額的
such a thing
這樣一個東西
Their materials do well is to say
他們的材料做到好的是說
in each band
在各個波段
This reflex is close to the time collar
這個反射力都接近時領
this is their material
這是他們的材料
made with fine
用細做的
This is outside the visible photon line
這個是在可見光子外線
follow up infrared band
跟進紅外線波段
This is the mid-infrared band
這個是中紅外線波段
just wave longer
就波上更長了
still very low
還是很低
And then to the far infrared
然後到了遠紅外線的話
got a little higher
稍微高一點起來了
This bankruptcy has been very long
這個破產已經非常長了
Until the microwave is relatively high
一直到微波才比較高
This material is such a
這個材料就是這樣一個通
Of course, microwaves are also available.
當然要做到微波也可以去來
It is also possible that its materials have to be further evolved
也可以 它的材料還要進一步進化
maybe they already have
也許他們已經有了
Didn't find them today
今天沒有找到他們了
That's the job of Academia Sinica
那這是中研院的工作
I think I am obliged to introduce the work of Academia Sinica today
我覺得我今天有義無介紹中研院的工作
so
所以
The second thing to talk about is
第二個來講的事情是
Heat management How to manage heat
熱的management 怎麼樣管理熱
these guys
這幾個傢伙
Managing heat is a master
管理熱是一級高手
Polar bears can survive temperatures as low as minus 50 degrees
北極熊可以在零下50度的溫度
life without problems
生活毫無問題
no problem at all
一點問題沒有
but
但是
yes it can
是它能夠
This is completely mentioned and does not spread out
這個完全提了不往外發散
you give you a hint of this
你給你一個這個暗示
If you take an infrared
你如果拿一個這個紅外線的
And the band is almost 10 micrometers
而且波段差不多在10個micrometer的
that infrared
那種紅外線
there is an infrared
就是有一個紅外線
Use that band to take pictures of the one in Beijing
那個波段去照那個北京的那種
They went to take pictures in the ice and snow
他們在冰天雪地去拍照
With visible light, you can still see Beijing
有可見光你還可以看到北京的
you use that infrared camera
你用那個紅外線照相機
you can't see
你照你看不到
except where its nose is
除了它鼻子鼻子的地方
you can see the nose
你可以看到鼻子
but the body can't see
但是身體看不到
is that it manages heat very well
就是它熱的管理非常好
Its temperature is the same as the ice coat next to it
它的溫度跟旁邊的冰衣
it even reflectivity
它甚至反射率
Infrared reflectivity is the same
紅外線反射率都一樣
it can do this
它可以做到這個地步
blood on that band
就血對那個波段
reflect with this
反射跟這個
its this fur
它的這個皮毛
this is its fur
這是它的毛
It also has thick subcutaneous death of course
它當然也有很厚的皮下死亡
It died 10 cm under the skin
它的皮下死亡10公分
then he is so thick
然後他這麼厚
subcutaneous wings
皮下翅膀
This is of course adiabatic
這當然是絕熱的
then on top is hair
然後在上面是毛
He has fur with a unique design on it
他有個毛上面有個獨特的設計
this is his hair
這是他一根毛
electron microscope
電子顯微鏡放打起來看
he is empty
他中間是空的
If we cut up human hair and look at it
我們如果把人的頭髮切起來看的話
go see that is real
去看那個是實心的
but
但是
polar bear hair
北極熊的那個毛
Looks like there are a lot of holes in the middle
看起來中間有很多空洞
The hair is transparent if you take it directly.
那個毛你直接拿來看是透明的
quite transparent hair
蠻透明的毛
A lot of transparent things accumulate on the body
很多透明的東西積在身體上
looks white
看起來是白的
this is no problem
這個沒有問題
Light range
隔接光範圍
But it's this hollow design
但是就是這個空洞的設計
makes his infrared
使得他的紅外線
This is the electromagnetic wave I just talked about
這個就是我剛剛講的電磁波
top down
從上頭下的
It's the same head now
現在是同比頭
fever
身體發熱
The temperature inside is 37 degrees
內部是37度的溫度
he has infrared
他有發紅外線
He makes a perfect greenhouse effect
他做一個完美的溫室效應
Infrared rays are emitted from the body
就是紅外線從身體發出來
completely blocked
完全被擋掉
The basic truth is this
基本的道理是這樣
it
它
Except for the hairy hollow, is it air?
除了這個毛中空那個是空氣嘛
so hot
所以就覺得熱
Heat conduction has this heat conduction and this heat radiation
熱傳導有這個導熱跟這個熱輻射
If it conducts heat, it relies on this hollow
導熱的話它就是靠這個中空
And relying on the casting of these pass buttons
還有靠這些傳扣的施放
This is the heat conduction itself
這是導熱本身
In addition, thermal radiation
另外就是熱輻射
Produced in
產生在
Its body temperature produces heat radiation that is about the same
它的體溫產生熱輻射就是差不多
The broken long infrared rays of 10 micrometers
10個micrometer的那個破長的紅外線
It's going to block that infrared ray
它要把那個紅外線擋掉
this is its body
這是它的身體
its heat source
它的熱源
The refractive index of infrared rays
對紅外線的折射率的話
gradually clear up
就逐漸剔透往上去
reduce
減少
to the last words
到最後的話
Infrared rays are always reflected back
紅外線就一直反射回來
every time there is
每次就有個
Equal reflection effect
等反射效果
I won't come out until the end
到最後就不出來了
Its body temperature can be maintained
它的體溫就可以保持
you can keep
就可以保持
This is light management
這個是光的管理
good
好
Another kind of light management is sea urchin
再講一種光的管理是海膽
sea ​​urchin is such a guy
海膽是這樣一個傢伙
The meat is delicious when you open it inside.
裡面打開來那個肉很好吃的
this is expensive chicken
這是雞品很貴的
this
這個
very expensive japanese food
很貴的日本菜
this creature
這個生物
it grows many times
它長很多次
it's very hard
這是非常硬
It's hard to back off
背不斷 很難背斷
carbon brick cover
是碳磚蓋
I'm probably talking about the structure inside the four
我大概在講四裡面的結構
it contains living organisms
它裡面是生物體
it's an animal on a gun
它是槍上動物
have mouth
有嘴巴
this is its mouth
這是它嘴巴
anal groove
肛門槽上
on the anal groove
肛門槽上的
It's counterclockwise and counterclockwise
它逆時是逆時底下的
mouth and teeth
嘴巴還有牙齒
Then you see four is this
然後你看到的四就是這個
ice cube long block four
冰塊長塊四
In addition it can be moved
另外它可以移動
it has this string
它有這個管柱
can move
可以動
I'm interested in this part
我有興趣的是這部分
if you touch it
你碰它的話
it will move immediately
它立會會動
That time will move the direction
那個次會移動方向
will be towards you
會朝向你
because you are the enemy
因為你就是敵人
it's facing you
它是要對著你
so you can't hold it
讓你沒辦法持它
can't move it
沒辦法動它
It's an optical fiber except this
除了這個以外它是一個光纖
it's a nice crystal
它是一個很好的晶體
Then the crystal pours light into it
然後這個晶體倒光進去
it is an optical fiber
它是一個光纖
The sea urchin turns into a shadow by this
海膽它靠這個變成陰影
There is an incentive to subsidize it
有補助它的動來
For example, a crab comes to eat
譬如說一隻螃蟹過來要吃
Crabs are powerful and will eat sea urchins
螃蟹很厲害會吃海膽
turn it over
把它翻過來
i dig inside
我挖裡面
But when it comes, there will be shadows
但是它一過來會有陰影
or the fish will have a shadow on it
或者魚在上面會有陰影
It adds this change of light
它就增設這個光的變化
I think the management of this light is very powerful
這個光的management我覺得很厲害
The three-layer cover
這三層蓋
If you go outside Taroko to step on the marble
如果你去外面太魯閣去踩大理石
Taroko, you only need one piece of this thing when you pick it up
太魯閣你拿起來這個東西就一塊
Call Calsan such a hard and solid thing
叫Calsan這樣一塊硬幫幫實心的東西
but sea urchin stone looks like this
但海膽石看起來是這個樣子
so
這樣
this is a short stone
這是一根很短的石
Then the barrel junction looks like this
然後這個桶結面看起來是這樣
This is a juvenile sea urchin
這個是幼稜的海膽
this is an adult
這個是成年的
it is a hole with many holes
它是一個有很多洞的
But the whole piece is a single body
但是呢整塊是一個單一經體
What is a single meridian body? That is, if you use X-rays on it
什麼叫單一經體?就是你用X光打它的話
to rap
去做饒舌
you see six o'clock
你看到就是六個點
not a ring
不是一個環
In other words, all scriptures and phases are consistent
換句話說裡面經相全部是一致的
a single body
排起來是一個單一經體
But obviously there's a lot of organic matter in there.
但是呢顯然裡面有很多有機物
clamped with it
跟它夾紮在一起
It forms a very unique single
它形成一種很獨特的單經
such a monotony
這樣的單經體
That's because there's a lot of organic matter in it
那因為裡面有很多有機物
makes it hard to break
使得它很難斷
You've eaten Bunker and you know it
你吃過Bunker你就知道
Bunker is better than this booth
Bunker比這個攤身
It's hard for you to bomb it with inorganic matter
你給它無機物彈的難的
It's hard, you can't hit it if you hit it vertically
很難 你用垂直砸就打不出
What is it, a lot of organic matter in the middle
就是什麼 中間很多有機物
Electricity will dissipate its power
電那裡面它的力量會分散掉
An inorganic, naturally occurring mineral
一塊無機的 從天然產的礦物
Hit it vertically and it will break
拿個垂直一敲就碎了
So it has a certain Indian
所以它有一定的印度
In addition it is a monolithic light
另外它是一個單金石的光
Yes delivery is very efficient
是 傳遞是非常有效率
So it's an organic and inorganic load
所以它是一個有機無機的負荷
Inorganic part is carbon brick cover
無機部分是碳磚蓋
The organic part is complicated
有機部分就複雜了
probably this glycoprotein
可能是這個糖類蛋白質
single body
單一經體
And then, a light guide
然後呢 是一個光傳導器
It is also a transmitter of feeling power
也是一個感覺力量的傳導器
Because it is hard, it is very sensitive to feel the force
因為它很硬 所以感覺力量是很靈敏的
There's something out there that feels as soon as it touches it
外面有一個東西一碰到它就感覺到
The laboratory wants to imitate
實驗室就想要去模仿
Is it possible to make this hole worry
能不能做出這個有孔洞的擔心
This is something I made in my lab
這是我實驗室做的一個東西
carbon brick cover
也是碳磚蓋
is in the form of a special carbon brick cover called Voltaire
是一個特殊碳磚蓋叫Voltaire的形式
it is hexagonal body
它是六方經體
Urea and glue
是用尿素跟膠水
In the small threshold, the collagen in Gelatin
在小專檻,在Gelatin這個膠原蛋白
It reacts at a high temperature of more than 100 degrees
在高溫100多度就反應
The economy made looks like a single catty
做出來的經濟看起來就是單斤
Then the X-ray evidence and Peng Huan's evidence know
然後X光的證據、彭寰的證據知道
It's the projectile, there's nothing wrong with it
是彈程概沒有錯
But this economic
但是這個經濟一看
open it up and take a closer look
打開來仔細一看
first time i see this next big jump
我第一次看到這個下一大跳
because of many holes
因為很多洞
the kind you know
就是你跟你認識的那種
The kind that helps a whole piece
那種幫忙一整塊的那個
The body is different
經體不一樣
it's obviously a pound
它明顯是一個單斤
because it has spirit and horns
因為它有靈有角
Spirit and horns
有靈有角
but there are many holes in it
但是裡面有很多洞
Those are the collagen I added
那些就是我加進去的膠原蛋白
After burning the collagen
把膠原蛋白燒掉以後就
find many holes
找出很多孔洞
Then I call it porous single catty
那我叫做多孔單斤
This is like the result of a sea urchin
這個就像海膽的結果了
You must have some
你身體上一定都會有一些
Kidney knots are, gallbladder knots are
腎結是、膽結是
there will be some points
會有一些點
just didn't grow up
只是沒有長大
When you grow up, you'll be in so much pain
長大的話你就痛得不得了
I need to see a doctor
就要看醫生了
Those deadlines are guts too
那些截止也都是膽金
But this apple meal lid
但是是這個蘋果膳蓋
They can make this kind of
他們在生物體可以做出這種
This kind of good optical properties
這種具有很好光學性質的
I'm not going to talk about his optical nutrition
我接下來就沒有談他的光學營養
Simply because he is guts
簡單就是因為他是膽金
A small relationship but a lot of holes in it
很小的關係 但裡面有很多孔
if the hole goes in something else
如果孔就會其他東西進去
you can sense him
你可以去感應他
do other things
做其他的事情
to say is to say
要講的就是說
Organisms manage this light very efficiently
生物體對這個光的管理是非常有效的
This is proof that he has guts
這就是證明他膽金
This uses the point of the electronic teacher
這個用電子老師的這個點
Next I will talk about gas management
接下來我要談氣體的management
what we just said
我們剛剛講的
If I want to make a fuel cell like that
我如果要做那樣的燃料電池
Or when it is solar battery of the decomposition of water
或者是水的分解的太陽的電池的話
I want to manage this gas
我要manage這個氣體
ah what to do
啊 怎麼辦
Let's take a look at the structure of a bird's lungs
我們來看看鳥的肺的結構
it's a bird's lungs
這是一個鳥的肺
Birds have the most powerful lungs of all living things
鳥是所有生物裡面肺的功能最強大的
the most powerful
最強大的
When this eagle is fighting
這個老鷹在打架的時候
there is a lot of air
是有大量的空氣
And they fly high
而且呢 它們飛得很高
the air is thinner
空氣比較稀薄
And some birds can fly as high as the Simara Mountains
而這個有些鳥可以飛到這個西馬拉山那麼高嘛
The density of air is only one-third of that of the earth's surface.
空氣密度只有地表三分之一吧
So its lung blood has a powerful function
所以它肺血是有強大的功能
The lungs are of course because of the exchange of air and blood
肺當然是因為進行這個空氣跟血液的交換
it is a two-fluid
它是一個雙流體
In terms of painters, it is a two-way fluid
在畫工來講是雙向流體
it has air bags
它有氣囊
Then there are many very thin
然後有很多很細很細的
Hierarchical structure of this pipeline
階層式結構的這個管道
air blood
空氣 血
Then what they cross is theirs
然後它們交叉的有的就是它們的
We do exchange the molecule O2
我們做進行交換O2這個分子
If you zoom in to see the details
那這個一個細部的放大起來看的話
you see it is
你看它是
It is the result of the concatenation formula I just mentioned.
就是我剛剛講的接成式的結果
It has the largest sac is the air sac
它有最大的囊子是氣囊
Then there are these spaces in the middle
然後呢有這麼比較中間的這些空間
there is even less space
還有更小的空間
space then the hole
空間然後這個洞
They conduct this flow of gas and liquid
它們進行這個氣體跟液體的流
There are some things that I can't figure out now. I'm not studying
就有一些我現在搞不清楚我不是學
Life I don't know which one is slippery and which one
生活我不知道哪一個是溜氣的哪一個
liquid
有液體的啦
so
這樣
The resolution diagram is like this
化解圖來是這樣
It is joined into the result of a large tube
它接成式的結果有大的管式
To a small tube, ah, a smaller tube
到小的管式啊更小的管式
Then do this air flow
然後進行這個空氣流
this is a blood vessel
這是血管
have
有
very effective this exchange
很有效的這個交換
From a rougher university
從比較粗的大學上
to this menace pavilion
到這個威脅館
do this
都進行這個
something like this
這樣的事
In terms of materials
材料上面來講
people just want to do
人們就想要做
This is a porous material
這種皆成是孔洞材料
We've had trouble using this so far
我們目前為止還很難用這個
What makes protein such a material
蛋白質什麼做出這樣的材料
Apparently creatures can do
顯然生物可以做
but we can always make inorganic
但我們總可以做無機物
Inorganic material
無機物材料
Our laboratory makes materials with many holes
我們實驗室做很多孔洞的材料
Its method is to take organic matter and inorganic matter
它的方法是拿有機物跟無機物
to self-install
去自主裝
This is completely self-installed
這是完全自主裝
one foot and it will form like this
腳一腳它就會形成這樣
This part is organic matter
這一部分是有機物
Then the next wall is
然後旁邊的牆壁是
Dioxide is inorganic and hard
二氧化系是無機物是硬的
Finally you put the organic matter inside
最後你把裡面的有機物
Burn off the collar or extract
燒掉衣柱或者萃取
you make the hole
你就做出孔洞了
the size of the hole
這個洞的大小
you can control
就可以控制
Using the molecular size of this organic
用這個有機物的分子大小
you control
你來控制
Available from two Nami
可以從兩個耐米
to maybe dozens of nami
到也許幾十個耐米
Such a medium porous material
這樣的一個中始度的孔洞材料
it's a water dragon coming out from corner to corner
它是一個水龍一角一角出來
So it has all sorts of hierarchical results
所以它有各式各樣階層式的結果
you can control
你可以去控制
I can't speak here today
我沒有辦法今天在這邊講
I just show you one
我只是讓你看一個
What does the electron micrograph look like
電子顯微電影圖看出來是怎樣
its hole
它的洞
This is from an interface to see it
這個是從一個界面來看它
This is to start a
這是啟動一種
It has a variety of one tube is bent
它有各式各樣的一個管是彎的
this is a straight tube
這個是直的管
This is the oxygen system
這個就是二氧化系
this is a hole
這個是洞
OK, what about the porous material?
好 孔洞材料呢
Can progress to class
可以進步做階層的
This is the one that the lab wants to imitate
這是實驗室裡面想要去模仿的一個
Hierarchical result approach
階層式的結果的作法
This paper is not my paper
這個一篇論文不是我的論文
this is
這個是
it does is a hierarchical
它做是一個階層式
A large amount of gas can be quickly dispersed inside
大量氣體可以在裡面很快分散出去
into the tiny hole
到很小的洞裡面
This gas is TNT
這個氣體是TNT
prevent explosives
防止炸藥
when passing the airport now
現在過機場的時候
they are most afraid of you
他們最怕你
yes there is this
是有這個
this dynamite
這個炸藥
TNT is an organic molecule
那TNT這種是有機分子
Three-way calculation plus this
三交計加本
This molecule is difficult for you to use
這個分子,你很難用
this
這個
abandoned to detect it
遺棄去偵測到它
The best way is to develop an artificial pen
最好的方法是發展一種人工筆
artificial brush
人工筆子
That artificial pen is very sensitive
那個人工筆很敏感
That is to say, your gas can
就是說你的氣體能夠
Scattered into a small hole, that small hole
分散到很小洞,那個小洞
run a detection version
進行一個偵測版本
Well, I'm not talking about the detection version here, I'm talking about it's a god-like structure
那我在這不講偵測版本,我是講說它是一個接神式結構
From Big Hole, Medium Hole to Small Hole
從大洞、中洞到小洞
This small hole is the size of a TNT molecule
這個小洞就是TNT分子這麼大小
It used it as a template when it was originally made
它原來做它的時候就用它做模板
This is the concept of template synthesis
這是模板合成的概念
I use it as a template when compositing, this is the red one
我用合成的時候用它做模板,就是這個紅的這塊
Other things that are silica
其它是二氧化系的東西
this template
這個模板
So when TNT comes
所以當TNT來的時候
It just snaps in and can suck a lot
它剛好就卡進去就可以吸很多量
No matter how big or small other molecules are,
其他分子大一點、小一點都不行
So it's very sensitive to selectivity
所以它選擇性很敏感的選擇性來
Then because it is a god-like structure
然後因為是接神式結構
From the big hole to the small hole in a short time
從大洞到小洞一下很快就
The past seems to be a life
散過去好像是一個生活
The purpose is the same as the lungs or many small holes in the nose
目的肺一樣或者鼻子很多小孔
it can be smelled at once
它一下就可以聞到
This is gas management
這是氣體的管理
used in this
用在這個
What I just said about batteries on carbon
我剛剛講的碳上電池的話
One of the things I just talked about is
我剛剛講的其中有一個是
The material is carbon
這個材料是碳
Then your porous carbon can also be made like this
那你多孔的碳也可以做成這樣
Like the one just now, it's a carbon dioxide system
像剛剛那個是二氧化系
this is carbon
這個就是碳
You can see that there are relatively large holes
你可以看到有比較大的洞
Then the big hole will be in the wall
然後大大的洞會在牆壁上
there are many small holes
有很多小洞
Also, have you seen the battery?
另外你電池有沒有看到是那個
inside the black and white part
那個黑白的部分裡面
there are even smaller holes
還有更小的洞
it is made of three
它是三個結成的
Let it load this Platinum Sharder on it
這上面讓它負載這個白金碎化劑
its this gas management is good
它的這個氣體管理很好
because big hole to small hole
因為大洞到小洞
In addition
另外呢
All these carbons are linked together
所有這些碳都連在一起
So its conductive path is connected
所以它導電的路徑是連的
no power outage
沒有斷電
It can be done like this to adjust the battery
它可以做這樣的話這樣調量電池
Then its current versus voltage is the best
然後它的電流對電壓作土龍是最好的
In comparison, activated carbon or platinum ridges can be used
比較起來能夠用活性碳或是用白金做的電脊
it performs much better
它的表現就好很多
This is a hierarchical bionic concept.
這個就是一個階層式的仿生的概念來做的
Of course it can be used as a reactor
那裡面當然可以做反應器
Our laboratory is in this Dadongqiao Cave
我們實驗室就在這個大東橋洞裡面
full of various catalysts
佈滿各式各樣的催化劑
then do the chemical reaction
然後去做化學反應
so soon
所以很快
react in a short time
短時間裡面進行反應
I won't talk about it
這我就不談了
Okay, let's talk about water
好 接下來談水
how water is managed
水怎麼管理
In a fuel cell just like that
在一個剛剛那樣的燃料電池
for example
譬如說
hydrogenation of oxygen to electricity
氧加氫變成電
Then it's water
然後產乎是水啊
Oxygen and hydrogen are poured in all the time
氧跟氫是一直灌進來
In fact, the water keeps coming out.
其實這個水就一直冒出來啊
How do you manage this water?
那這個水你要怎麼管理
is also an important thing
也是一個重要的事情
if you don't manage
如果你不去管理
it blocks everything
它把所有的東西堵起來了
It will be more stressful to come in again
要再進來就更大壓力
you spend more
你就耗更多
your efficiency will decrease
你的效率就會降低
or at the end
或者到最後就
can't stay at all
根本就留不動了
stay in many places
很多地方都留不動
those with tiny holes
微小孔的那些
To manage the flow of this water
就要管理這個水的流動
this is a problem
這是一個問題
Well, we've just talked about this compounding effect
那我們剛剛已經談到這個合化效應
The compounding effect is one
合化效應就是一個
One way to manage water well
很好管理水的一個方法
right
對不對
let's see
我們來看看
how from there
怎麼樣從那裡
release to be bright
放生來得到明亮
Let's look at the lotus leaf again
我們再來看一下荷葉
lotus leaf words
荷葉的話
it's a drop
它是一個水珠
can be on this lotus leaf
可以在這個荷葉上面
this slide
這個滑動
The reason is the so-called contact angle
原因就是所謂接觸角
Very big
非常大
it's not collapsed
它不是坍平的
but rolled up
而是捲起來
rolled up state
捲起來的一個狀態
why is it like this
它為什麼會這樣
Because it is related to this structure
因為就是跟這個結構有關
its a lot raised fog
它很多凸起霧
let's see
我們來看看
This so-called supertransportation
這個所謂產生的一個叫做超輸水作用
A strong wall of clear water
清水的一強壁
like glass
譬如說玻璃
Glass is a strong wall of clear water
玻璃是個清水的強壁
just water will
就是水就會
Spread it flat and become a thin layer of water film
攤開來 平的變成薄薄的一層水膜
If you pour water, say spicy
如果輸水的話就說辣
if you put a spicy surface
你放一個辣的表面的話
it will become a semicircle
它會變成一個半圓
or something more than a semicircle
或者是更超過半圓的東西
But there is still an angle
但是還是有個角度啦
That angle won't be 180 degrees
那個角度不會到180度
it will be there and stick there
它會在 然後就黏在那裡不動
If a glass is heavily oiled
如果一個玻璃上面沾了很多油
just can't get oil
就是乾不進油
see a lot of water sticking to it
看很多水 黏在上面
on the leaf of the plant
那植物的那個葉子上面
Of course it feels oily
固然感覺是油油的
it's already a bit of a loser
它已經是有點輸的
But it's not enough to say let that
但是不足夠說讓那個
that thing
那個東西
That droplet is easily in the liberalization
那個水滴就很容易在自由化中
it further this structure
它進一步的這個結構
There are all kinds of talk here
還有各式各樣在這邊講
This is the so-called Cassi state
這一個所謂Cassi state的這個
That is to say, it is easier for us to understand
也就是說我們比較容易來理解
That is to let this water
那就是讓這個水
Go to bed of nails for that yogi guru in india
去做印度人的那個瑜伽大師的釘床
isn't a yoga guru a lot of bed of nails
瑜伽大師不是很多釘床嗎
that has a lot of nails on it
那個上面很多釘子
Then the master lay down
然後那個大師就躺上去了
You hang it vertically, what are you doing?
你拿到垂直上面垂啊 幹什麼
right
對不對
Then we just let the water
那我們就是讓這個水
Drops of water to make this bed
水滴去做這個丁床
when he was in bed
他這個丁床的時候
he doesn't want to go down
他不願意下去
Because the surface tension
因為下去這個表面張力
too much energy not to slip out
能量太不滑出來
he won't go down
他不下去
If he doesn't go down, he will roll up.
不下去他就上面滾吧
This is what causes the so-called superspeed water benefit
這就是造成所謂超速水效益
if the plant is on that lotus leaf
植物在那個荷葉的話
Basically this is enough
基本上這個就夠
But if the lotus leaf goes further
但是荷葉進一步的話
is the combination of these two Nami
是結合這兩個耐米的
with micron
跟微米的
This is its micron scale
這個是它的微米尺度
This is the scale of difficulty
這是難米尺度
it combines two
它把兩個結合在一起
This water transfer is more efficient
這個輸水效益更好
I won't talk about the details there
細節我就不在那邊講
don't talk too much over there
不在那邊多講
This is to introduce
這個要介紹
The other one is that you say it slides
另外一個是你說它的滑動
if there is something on it
如果上面有張東西
is a plain spicy surface
是一個普通的辣的表面
it or glass surface
它或者玻璃表面
It will stick and stay still
它就會黏著張動不動了
it doesn't move at last
它最後不動
But if it's a speeding water like this
但是如果是一個像這樣超速水
it not only understands
它不但懂
And it will take the tension away
而且會把張動不分走
So the filthy bastard dripped to the roll
所以汙蛋那個水滴到滾
This oneness shows that it is clean
這個合一表明是乾淨的
very clean without dust
很乾淨 不會有灰塵
So we say that you will not be stained by the fog
所以我們說出霧你而不染
So there's a lot of application here
所以呢 這裡有很多應用價值
For example, the lenses of your glasses
譬如說你的眼鏡的鏡片
with superfast water on it
上面具有超速水的
so you don't get foggy
所以你就不會起霧
your camera
你的照相機
Best Camera Lenses Top Now
現在最好的照相機鏡頭上面
treated with ultra-fast water
就經過超速水的處理
It won't get foggy if it gets water droplets on it
它不會 上面沾水滴就不會有霧
The next thing I want to introduce is the work of Academia Sinica
接下來我要介紹的是中研院的工作
It belongs to Dr. Chen Peilin from the Ink Center
是這個印克中心陳培林博士的
he's here ask him a question
他在這裡 有問題問他
He just figured out how to do it in this one
他就想辦法在這個一個
The solid surface makes that like a lycium
固體表面做出那個像合花的
raised structures on leaves
葉子上面凸起的結構
The method is to use this sphere implicit in a script
方法是用一個劇本隱悉的這個圓球
can be made into a very uniform ball
可以做得很均勻的圓球
then use this
然後用這個
this
這個
It should be Shi Wen's.
應該是石溫的吧
This plasma allows the plasma to eliminate sugar
這個電漿 讓電漿去消糖
remove sugar
去消糖
Little Five Seconds looks like this
小五秒看來是這樣的
smaller than look
比看看小一點
It disappears like this in fifty seconds
像五十秒就消成這樣
Then you look like a spit
那你就看起來是一個一個吐氣物
If you continue to eliminate, you will exhale more
繼續消就會更吐氣
so
這樣
Then
然後
departmental complex
上面有進行部別複雜
It has ribs that modify the surface
它上面有修飾表面的筋
Then there is the flow
然後有流存
I won't go into that detail
那個細節我就不講
the point is
重點就是
After these plasma demagnetization
經過這些電漿消磁以後
cause a lot of aspirates
造成很多吐氣物
Finally, from the contact angle
最後可以從接觸角
It's the original shape of 115 degrees.
是原來一百一十五度這樣的形狀
to the last one hundred and fifty one
到最後一百五十一
Actually it can do 170 degrees maybe
事實上可以做到一百七十度也許
But it's hard to do 190 degrees
但是一百九度很難做
Rolled away because of a slight shock
因為稍微震動就滾走了
Three rolls of that thing
那個東西就三個滾
That's the butt bed effect
那就是這個丁床效應
butt bed effect
丁床效應的話
under different cutting conditions
在不同的切削狀況
if its exhalation condition is different
它的吐氣狀況不一樣的話
The contact angle ended up being close to 180 degrees
接觸角度最後接近一百八十度
this is a
這個是一個
bound
綁身的
concept to do
概念來做的
When he was almost unified
那在差不多他統一的時候
Chen Peining this job
陳培寧這個工作
In addition, the future of Chinese scientists
另外被中國科學人的將來
He later made great achievements in this field
他後來這個領域做得非常大
They use various tests
他們用各種各樣的試驗
Chemistry collaborators make closer to that
化學合作人做出更接近那個
the lotus
那個蓮花的
The structure of the synthetic surface
合化表面的結構
he uses this
他是用這個
He uses an electrical method
他是用一個電方法
So make a polymer square
所以做高分子電方
or make a ball to many divisions
或做出球給很多師
he can do well
他可以做得很好的
this
這個
this drop of water is on top
這個水珠在上面
arrangement of carbon tubes
也要用碳管的排列
This is the one from Beijing Academy of Sciences
這個是北京科學院的這個
main road book
主道本
carbon nanotubes
他就用納米碳管
there is another one that does
還有一個做的
It's also the top bed
也是頂床嘛
This is more like the top bed of an Indian master
這更像印度大師的頂床
let the bottom be on top
讓水底在上面
Then work is what I can control
後來工作就是我可以控制
i can control him
我可以控制他
I see the surface
我看那個表面呢
turn into crisp water
一下變成酥水
super crisp water
超酥水
Turn into ultra-clear water at once
一下變成超清水
Just spread some ingredients on top
就是上面鋪一些份子
this guy
這個份子
to this thing outside
對外面這個東西
let it fall
讓它倒下去
This section is backwater
它這一段就是溯水
then the whole will be out of water
那整個就會超出水
In addition to the puzzling structure just mentioned
加上剛剛講的那種難迷結構
for which the structure will exceed
對 它結構就會超出
Then when it stops, it's clear water
然後它停起來的話就是清水
So this water will be collected and turned into a ball once it is dipped in water.
所以這個水一下沾一下都收起來變球
Very precise control over water
對水可以做很精確的控制
For example, this is the contact angle
譬如說這是接觸角
Contact angle
接觸角
Then this Cosmite can do the control of this track
然後這個Cosmite它可以做這個萊軌的控制
After this electrical control
經過這個電控制
Or PH control can be done
或者PH控制這都可以做得到
This is an example of an electrical control
這是一個電控制的例子
A liquid approaches 180 degrees from the contact angle
一個液體從接觸角接近180度
Change the voltage with control
改變電壓有控制
fall
倒
spread out
攤下去
many degrees
很多程度
That
那
of course japanese
當然日本人
sell it quickly
趕快就拿來賣
Japan combined light blowing agent
日本結合的光吹化劑
What is produced is ultra-clear water and super-water
做出來的就是有超清水跟超出水的
On the surface this is super salary
表面這是超薪水的
can make this surface very smooth
可以讓這個表面很光滑
So if it is reflected in the rearview mirror of the car, it will not fog up
所以在著汽車的後視鏡反射的話就不會起霧
good
好
just that particle
剛剛那個粒子
haven't really used it yet
都還沒有真正用到
I originally spoke about this fuel cell
我最初講這個燃料電池的關於
its management
它的管理
But it shouldn't be possible to imagine
但是應該不能來想像
what can be done
可以做什麼
the flowing water
就是那些流通的水
Make super pay for the water when it pours
水倒的時候給它做出超薪水
Then its gas flow and liquid flow will not block each other
那它的氣體的流動跟液體的流動就不會互相擋了
Because it, the liquid is suspended on some hollows
因為它這個液體是懸浮在一些空洞的上面
gas flow
氣體的流動
nose does not interfere heavily
鼻子不會嚴重乾涉
No blocking, no flotting
不會堵 不會flotting
Batteries made in a pro-family reaction
在一個親家養的反應做成電池
produce water, this water can
產生水這個水都可以
very easy
很容易
because it slides easily
因為它滑動的很容易
it can flow
它就可以流動
So in doing the management
所以在這樣做的management
water management
水的management
Apparently that should also help
顯然應該也會有幫助
Finally I'll talk about catalysts
最後我會講講到催化劑
you want to do this
你要做這個東西
What is the most basic chemical reaction
最基本的化學反應是什麼
there is a chemical reaction
有個化學反應
new example
新例子
becomes H2
變成H2
right? get electrons get electrons from electrodes
對不對 獲取電子 從電極獲取電子
Or H2 conversely means that H2 becomes a new example
或者H2反過來講就是H2變成新例子
Then the new example has to be traditionally ground to the other end
然後新例子要傳統的磨到另外一頭
Then H2 becomes a new example is the lost electron
然後H2變成新例子就是丟的電子
To do this thing, that depends on a shattered body
要做這件事情 那個靠一個碎化體
I was talking about platinum
剛剛講的是白金
I pay more attention to the oxygen head on the other end.
另外一頭我比較注重是氧類頭
Oxygen headers are also
氧類頭也是
Oxygen O2
氧O2
The first thing it needs to accept electrons to become O2-
第一件事情它要接受電子 變成O2-的因理
that's the first step
那是第一步
Then step by step it becomes
然後再一步一步下去變成
Platinum is too expensive
那個用白金化太貴了
What we just said, if it is really made of platinum
我們剛剛講的如果真的用白金做
we can't go on
我們做不下去了
This is what the sun can't do
這已經太陽的事情就做不成了
Because the reserves of platinum on the earth are simply not enough
因為地球上的白金的儲量根本就是不夠
effective number
效數
Organisms have long been able to manage this oxygen
生物體早就會manage這個氧
BOSS movement
BOSS的運動
All of us breathe in oxygen
這個這些我們的人的呼吸都吸進來氧
we do things with it
我們拿它來做事情
I'm here to talk about a relatively simple
我在這邊講一個比較簡單的
This is what our lab is doing
這個是我們實驗室在做的
It's really easier to do
真的做的比較簡單
It is not just H2 plus O2 to change water directly
它不是直接剛剛的H2加O2變水
I just do a simple response is this
我是只做一個簡單反應是這個
O2 receives an electron to become superoxide
O2接收一個電子變成超氧
This superoxide is receiving electrons to turn into hydrogen peroxide in two instructions
這個超氧是在接收電子在兩個指示變成雙氧水
There is a efficacious number that looks like this
有個效數長成這個樣子
It's called SOD
它就叫SOD
super oxo coal
超氧齊化煤
it is a coal
它是一個煤
Of course, other effects can be used later to turn this into water and oxygen.
當然後面可以其他效數繼續把這個變成水跟氧
Then I can raise it and then dig it up.
然後能養再去挖過來說
Its last can turn O2 into H2
它最後的可以把O2變成H2
This is a reaction to the grading we just talked about
這是我們剛剛講定級上的一個反應
It's Yang Ji's reaction
就是楊吉那邊的反應
I don’t need the common people to tell me to help me make an effect
我可以不用百姓講幫我做一個效
But this effect, if you really take it seriously
但是這個效數你真正認真來講
It feels like you have to raise a lot of big factories
你要養很多大廠的感覺
Then go to performance
然後去表現效數
That is also an important thing
那個也是貴的要事
Is there a way we can make a compound
我們有沒有辦法做一個化合物
That compound mimics this potency
那個化合物模仿這個效數
This is bionic
這就仿生了
If you make this compound to imitate this effect
做這個化合物模仿這個效數的話
Then let's see the effect
那我們就來看看這個效數
What's the result in the middle
中間是什麼結果
It doesn't matter what this page does to protein and what to us
它這頁對蛋白質的這個對我們不管
Let's look at the middle one
我們看最中間這個
on the next page
在下一頁
it's here
在這裡
This is the only chemical structure that appears in my entire speech
這個是我這整個演講中唯一出現化學結構
I'm sorry if you don't study chemistry imitation
對不起 如果你不是學化學模仿
I only focus on a copper
我只重點來講說有個銅
There's copper with a bunch of protein molecules in the middle
有個銅 中間有一堆蛋白質分子
there today
今天在那裡
Focus on this
重點來這個
This copper is the center of its active point
這個銅是它的效數活性點的中心
I just talked about this super sheep molecule
剛剛講這個這個超羊分子
Souff Osley reacted to him and became O2
舒芙奧斯萊跟他反應變成O2
B has O2 coming out
B有O2出來
copper becomes copper
銅變成一架銅
Then it becomes H2O2 with another long-term oxygen molecule.
再跟另外一個長氧分子變成再加持著變成H2O2
The reaction I'm talking about now is this
我現在講的這個反應就是這個
Haven't used that electrical response yet
還沒有用到那個電氣反應上面
The electrical reaction requires the final change to water
電氣反應需要最後變到水
let's start with this
我們先講到這個
Half of it is made by this Mars point
一半它是靠這個火星點來做的
But carefulness on the side is absolutely necessary
但是旁邊的細心絕對必要
And this bridge to achieve such a central point
還有這個橋來達成這樣一個中心點
The large pile of amine bricks next to it finally surrounded a very complicated result
旁邊那一大堆胺基磚最後就圍起來一個很複雜的結果
then we want to say
那我們就想說
I first synthesize a molecule
我先合成一個分子
like this part
像這一部分
and placed inside a porous material
然後放在一個孔洞材料裡面
like the outside part
像外面那一部分
I typed it like this
我這樣把它打成這樣
Here is my bionic method
這是我的仿生方法
we won't talk about the details
這細節我們就不多談
Chemosynthesis looks like a bit of a nuisance
化學合成看起來是有點討厭
But it's not difficult
但是其實不難
it's my hole
就是我洞
that hole
那個洞
Didn't I just say that I make hole materials
我剛剛不是講我做孔洞材料
delivery is possible
接生是可以
Gas fluid enters quickly
氣體流體很快的進入
Then these molecules loaded are my
然後負載的這些分子就是我的
mimic the molecule that eliminates
模仿那個消除的分子
it's going to be my catalyst
它要做我那個催化
its synthesis gas has pentagon
它的合成氣體有五角
I'm afraid I won't go into the details of its catalytic reaction here.
它的催化反應細節我恐怕也不在這裡多講了
This is what you will talk about if you are in the chemistry semester
這是如果在化學期的話都會去講它
it is a circular reaction
它是一個循環反應
the point is to say
重點是說
This will be disconnected when the reaction is in the middle
反應在中間的時候這個會斷開的
This chemical room needs to be disconnected
這個化學間要斷開
If this molecule is in aqueous solution, it will not be able to do work.
如果在水溶液這個分子就做不下去功了
this loop won't run
這個循環跑不了
because it has to be picked up again
因為它要再接回去的
It won't work if you take it back
要接回去就不行了
Just break up, break up, run away
就斷了就分家了就跑了
But I use this hole to lift it
但是我用這個洞把它掀著
I just imitate it. The simple pendulum is the skeleton.
就是我模仿它單擺是骨架
like this
這樣子的話
i produce
我產生
Use this molecule to sense this Super Oxide
用這個分子去感應這個Super Oxide
Super Oxide is a
Super Oxide是有一個
produced by an enzyme reaction
酵素反應產生的
I'm going to generate this superoxide molecule
我去產生這個超氧分子
to generate light
去照光產生
Then detect with this
然後用這個偵測
The way we detect its activity is by saying
我們偵測它的活性的方法是說
How much catalytic converter is needed
需要多少的催化器的量
can cut it in half
可以把它降到一半
This is called IC50
這個叫IC50
IC50 Let's do 0 hours and 20
IC50 我們去做0個鐘頭跟20個
IC50 means that the higher the worse
IC50的意思就是說越高越差
because you need a lot of catalyst
因為你需要大量的催化器
to achieve the same effect
去達到同樣的效果
the higher the worse
越高越差
This is our catalyst itself
這個就是我們的催化器本身
did not do other things
沒有去做其他的事情
didn't let go and didn't do anything
沒有放動也沒有幹什麼
it's inactive
它一下就沒活性了
And the activity is not good
而且活性不好
50%
50%
After a design of the material which moves in various ways
經過各式各樣都動的材料的設計
side mimic protein
還有旁邊模仿蛋白質
surrounding structure
周邊的構造
try to imitate it
盡量去模仿它
because we know protein
因為我們知道蛋白質
the result of that pin count
那個銷數結果
I can get down to 1.9 at my best
我做到最好的時候可以降到1.9
Of course, this is not as good as the real effect.
這個當然還比不上真正的效果
This real effect has an IC50 of 0.9
這個真正的效果有IC50是0.9
already very very good
已經非常非常好了
Then I want to tell you one thing is to say
那我要告訴你一件事情就是說
don't you use platinum
你不要用白金嘛
you do this
你做這個事情
It's the reduction reaction
就是養的這個還原反應
originally was
本來就是
what all animals do
所有動物都會做的事情
Why are you going for platinum?
你為什麼要去搞白金來做
should go this way
應該是走這一條路
but now
但是現在
Almost no one goes this way yet
還幾乎沒有人走這一條路
But I think it will be needed in the future
但是我覺得是將來需要
a path that needs to be taken
必要需要走的一條路
I won't talk about the details
這個細節我都不講了
This is a lot of material
這個很多材料
Various Designs for Being Human
做人的各種各式樣的設計
i'm not going to be here today
我不打算今天在這裡
good
好
The final overall effect is this
最後總的效果就是這樣
he reacted
他做了這個反應
use one
用一個
simulated artificial effect
模仿生的人工效數
to achieve this
來達成這個樣子
add in small portions
用小的份子加上
Kong Dong's material
孔東的材料
Of course next we should do this
當然下一步我們應該做這個
Convert this again to one-half of the feed water
把這個再轉換成二分之一的養家水
The other level of response is the new
那另外一級的反應就是新
it all adds up to
全部加起來就是
I want to finally make this Fuel Electronics Singayang
我要最後打成這個燃料電子新加洋
Generate this electricity and water
產生這個電跟水
Of course it's still early
這個目標當然還早
But this is a bionic idea
但是這是一個仿生的思路
rather than an idea with an industrial catalytic period
而不是一個用工業催化期的想法
Ok, finally I should make a short structure
好 最後呢我應該做一個簡短的結構
what i'm talking about today is
我今天在講的是
Using Power in an Energy Problem
用力量在一個能源的問題
our generation
我們這個世代
and the problem that the next generation may face
及下一個世代可能都面臨的這個問題
We will eventually convert to the sun's
我們最後要轉換成太陽的
We're going to design a chemical solar electron
我們要設計一個化學的太陽電子
convert solar energy into chemical
把太陽能轉換成化學的
or fuel electronics
或者是燃料電子
convert to sunny
先轉換成晴
which is then converted into electricity
然後再轉換成電
The problem faced is to manage the light
以面臨的問題是要管理光
Facing problems to manage water
面臨問題要管理水
Facing Problems To Manage Gas
面臨問題要管理氣體
also manages catalytic
還管理催化
every step i think
所有每一步我都認為
can be done with bionic methods
都可以用仿生辦法來做到
all can
全部都可以
If that day comes, we should do it very cheaply
如果到那一天我們應該是做得很便宜很便宜的
to use the sun
來利用太陽的
At that time there was a second process
那個時候就有一個第二個過程
Come out and build a big project to do these things
出來蓋很大的工程來做這些事情
produce it
把它生產出來
I don't expect it to be built any time soon
我不預料它會很短期能打造
But it's worth sitting here and thinking about it
但是值得在座住位去好好想
Especially the Academia Sinica should have a lot of energy to do this
尤其中研院應該很大的能量可以做這個事情
Before doing this, we need to know a lot of things
做這個事情之前我們需要很多事情要了解
because it is a design
因為它是一個設計
The principle of design What is the design principle of bionics
設計的原理 仿生的設計原理是怎麼樣
we need to understand it
我們需要去了解它
we don't just look at it
我們不只是看它長相
Sometimes you look at its appearance for a long time
有時候你看它半天長相
I really don't know what it does
真不知道它幹什麼
Like the fine algae just mentioned
像剛剛講的細藻那個東西
you see it looks beautiful
你看它長相很漂亮
but don't know what it does
但不知道它幹什麼
Principles of Design
設計的原理
In addition, I am afraid that not all of them are self-installed.
另外呢 恐怕不是全部是自主裝
Creatures are all self-installed
生物是全部自主裝
Self-loading from the bottom up
從下而上自主裝上來
We may also have to go from top to bottom
我們可能還要從上而下
some designs
一些設計
these combined
這些組合起來
Of course these things are cross-cutting
當然這些東西是跨領域的
chemistry physics biology
化學物理生物
Co-layer
共層
the last one
最後是一個
Combination across domains
跨領域的結合
such a thing
這樣一件事情
i think it's
我覺得這是
an idea i'd love
一個想法我很樂意
family language propaganda
家語宣揚
convey
傳達
The last word is about the students
最後的話就講到說學生
how did you do it
怎麼樣下手的
to do these interdisciplinary learning
去做這些跨領域的學習
some things i'm doing now
有些事情我現在正在做的
do this
是做這個
middle school textbook
國中的教科書的
design
設計
my Ministry of Education said
我教育部說
Although my Ministry of Education does not sell books
我教育部雖然不賣書
But they are developing teaching materials
但是他們有在發展教材
never done well
始終沒有做好是把
I think it is not put this
我認為是沒有把這個
A good combination of life technology and natural science
生活科技跟自然學科結合好
You now know that there is nature in the country
你們現在知道國中有自然
and living technology
與生活科技
Then everyone recognizes life technology
那大家認知生活科技
public welfare
就是公益
nature is physics
自然就是物理
physical chemistry lesson by lesson
物理化學一課一課的
In fact, Guo Zhongyou did the same thing.
事實上郭忠祐也是這樣搞
just deal with the mage
只是應付法師
but
但是
You have to be the last to enter the battle
登陣你要做到最後就是
The basic principles of physical chemistry biological
物理化學生物這些基本原理
and how did he design a thing
以及他到底怎麼設計出來一個東西
His design in a living organism is
在一個生物體裡面的他的設計是
very complicated very complicated
很複雜很複雜
we have some design ideas
我們有一些設計的想法的話
in student education
在學生教育裡面
I think it's quite necessary
我覺得是蠻必要的
if it can be integrated
如果能夠把它整合起來
learn early
很早就學習
New Year's Eve Music Learning
跨年音樂學習
and then do this comparison
然後進行這個比較
The so-called integrative biology
所謂 integrative biology
Integrative Biology Words
整合的生物學的話
Finally a wonderful infrastructure
最後很美妙的基建
Fantastic applications may develop
很美妙的應用可能會發展出來
ok i will stop here today
好我今天就講到這裡
Finally, thank you Nie Ting
最後謝謝各位的聶庭
and many of my collaborators
還有我很多很多的合作者
and my students
以及我的學生
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
There's still a lot of time
還有這個蠻多的時間
If you want to ask a certain teacher
假如大家要請教某老師
He's at Nanotech and this
他在奈米科技還有這個
this benefit
這個效益方面的
concept words
觀念的話
let's open the discussion first
我們先來開放討論
ask a professor
請教某教授
About your nano-bionic materials
有關你奈米仿生材料
Is it for our human body
是不是對我們人體
suffering from bone
患有骨頭
What do patients with this disease have
這個疾病的患者有什麼
What are the benefits?
好處有什麼可行的作用
Thanks
謝謝
i'm not a doctor
我不是醫生
So I'm afraid I can't say
所以我恐怕沒有辦法說
directly to a patient
直接對一個病患
I can only talk about it from the point of view of material concept
我只能講說從材料觀念往來講
If he wants to be a material senior
他是要做一個材料學長的話
The last thing he might have done was an artificial skeleton
他最後可能打得做的是一個人工骨骼
we are all now
我們現在都
with artificial bones
有人工骨骼
material artificial bone
材料人工骨骼
Mainly too metal and metal
主要是太金屬和金屬
But one day maybe we can emulate it a little better
但是有一天也許我們可以模仿得更好一點
it is relatively light
它是比較輕的
and from time to time technology
而且不時技術
Maybe it's something like bones with zero calcium acid and slowly do it
可能是零酸鈣的像骨頭這樣的東西慢慢去做
But it's still far away
不過目前還距離很遠
At present, Taihe gold is used to make artificial bones
目前都是用太和金做人工骨骼
But the surface treatment is to prevent kidney
但是表面處理是要防腎
make it biocompatible
讓它跟生物的相容性
If this is to that extent
如果這個是到那個地步的話
Materials used
用到材料
if not to that point
如果沒有到那個地步
Of course you should eat more calcium
你當然應該多吃一些鈣
eat more vitamins
多吃一些維他命
dorsese sun
多塞塞太陽
This is quite necessary
這個是蠻必要的
we see the same creatures
我們看到同樣的生物
words like bones
像骨頭的話
It can grow as big as Konglong
它可以長得像孔龍那麼大
It can be as small as a mouse bone
也可以像小老鼠骨頭那麼小
you see that algae now
你現在看到那個細藻
it has a very complex structure
它有一個很複雜的結構
Then there's no way we'll find that
那我們可不可能去找到那個
Like that factor that makes the bones grow and shrink
像那個骨頭讓它長大縮小的那個因素
Scale up that slender structure
把那個細長的結構換大縮小
to the size we want to apply
到我們自己想要的尺寸來應用
if i knew how the lab did it
假如我知道實驗室怎麼去做它的話
Maybe it can, but the creature has a certain size
也許可以 但是生物它就一定的Size
Slender is a single celled organism
細長是單細 單細胞生物
Its creatures are born so small
它的生物產生出來就是那麼小
micron, but human words are far, far away from this
micron的 但是人的話離這個很遠很遠
to make such a good structure
要做出那麼好的結構
I at least admit I don't know how to make it up
我至少我承認我不知道怎麼做起來
We have to make a big decision
我們要做出一個很大的刻意
it's a mess it has holes
就是亂七八糟的它有洞
but the shape is ugly
但是形狀的很醜陋
No it's not easy to control it's that big
沒有 不是很容易控制的 那麼大
Our control is from small to high
我們的控制是從小的越上來
The harder it is to control, most people think that
越難控制 一般人會想法是說
big good control no
大的好控制 不是
Because if it wants to be self-assertive, use chemistry to let it be self-assertive
因為如果要自主張 用化學放它自主張
It's getting harder and harder to control
有越上來越難控制
i mean
我的意思是說
Konglong like the same bone
像同樣骨頭的孔龍
it can grow so big
它可以長那麼大
The mouse has such a small bone
老鼠它的骨頭那麼小
between them to control it
那它們之間控制它
Factors that can grow so big
能夠長那麼大的因素
or long so small factor
或者長那麼小的因素
There should be a mechanism
應該是有一個機制
It must have a genetic component
它一定有基因的因素
there is a mechanism
有一個機制
That mechanism can be found
那個機制是可以找出來
and then apply it to something else
然後來應用到別的東西的
words in a way
在某種程度的話
We genetically modify
我們用基因改造
Can make a bigger animal benefit
可以做出大一點的動物效益
But this is still somewhat limited
但這都還是有某種程度的限制
perhaps
大概
But the control of our creatures
但是我們這種生物的控制
We don't do it casually, do we?
我們不隨便去做它對不對
There is also this ethical issue
還有這個倫理的問題
these questions
這些問題
But if we talk about experimental flow synthesis
但是如果說是實驗化流合成
there is no way
都沒有辦法
Because this is what I just said
因為這個我剛剛講過就是
I don't know what you mean by creature control
我不知道你指生物的控制
Biocontrol for genetic modification
生物控制做基因改造
yes to some extent
是某種程度是有的
have
有
Even if it is good, I just want to ask
就算好 我是想請問一下
I just saw it in a header
剛我在一張頭裡面上面有看到
There is a picture about that ultraviolet light
就是有一張關於那個紫外線
its effect on the surface properties of the object
它對物體表面特性改變的結果
like the surface of carbon dioxide
好像是二氧化碳的表面
Then it should be in that
然後應該是在那個
Changes in water clarity and water transport
清水性和輸水性變化的
it is a molecule above
它是上面一個分子
That molecule deforms when it shines light on it
那個分子照光它會變形
That head is a molecule of oil
那個頭是油的分子
it stands up and feels like oil
它站起來感覺是油
and then give it the overdrive result
然後再給它做超速的結果
It's more oily and more watery
就更油 更輸水
But if you turn on the power
但是假如你通電以後
Its molecular deformation will come down like this
它分子變形會這樣下來
Exposed is another form of molecule
暴露出來是另外一個形式的分子
it can do this
它可以這樣做
So this charge
所以這扣電
In addition, pH control is also available
另外有PH控制也可以
it can control a surface
它可以控制一個表面
To change its water-clearing and water-transmitting properties
去改變它的清水性跟輸水性
Hello, Mr. Mono, I just want to ask for advice
Mono老師您好 那個就是想請教一下
Just like you do with the refugee materials
就是像你們做那些難民材料的話
Like controlling the PH value
像控制那PH值的話
Would it make a difference that
是不是會造成不同的那個
The body size is different like this
經體大小不同這樣
That is, relatively speaking, the pH value is important for living things.
那就是相對來講PH值對生物的話
Will it affect him?
它這樣會有影響嘛
Then another question is to say
然後另外一個問題是說
If you are making refugee material
像在製作難民材料的話
Like now maybe doing some chemical batteries like this
像現在可能是做一些化學電池這樣
If it is really applied to the human body
那如果說真正應用到人體的話
during its manufacture
在它製造過程中
like some refugee particles would say
像一些難民的顆粒會不會說
some powder layers during the manufacturing process
在製造過程中一些粉層
cause harm to a person
造成一個人體的危害
Even when it is really applied to the human body
甚至說它真的應用到人體的時候
can't be ruled out
沒辦法被排除
Let’s talk about refugees’ impact on the human body
要講說難民對人體的
the bad words
這個壞處的話
I really don't know a lot of things now
現在很多東西的確是不知道
You just don't want to eat indiscriminately.
你反正不要亂吃東西就是了
Then what I'm talking about doesn't apply to the human body.
那我講的東西並不是用到人體
i don't have today
我沒有今天
I'm not talking about medicine tomorrow
我明天沒有在講藥
what you'll swallow when you make the wrong food
做錯食物你會吞的東西
all on one device
都做在一個器件上
that should be fine
那應該還好
we don't just try
我們不隨便去試
It's a battery, right?
它是一個電池嘛對不對
this part
這個這部分
still good
還是好
But it's true that biological control is on the way
但是的確生物體控制奔領畢
Bi our laboratory control is much higher
畢我們實驗室控制高很多
Our laboratory can change the pH arbitrarily
我們實驗室可以任意變換PH
What is the difference in the configuration of the material made by different pH
是不同的PH做出來的材料構型什麼不一樣
Biology doesn't have that many options
生物的話沒有那麼多選擇
Its PH is around seven o'clock
它PH它就在七點幾左右
but it can do so many things
但它可以做那麼多事
it can still be controlled to
它還是可以控制到
Many chemical reactions if in neutral
很多化學反應如果在中性的時候
hard to do can't do it
很難做做不出來
but it has no valid number
但是它沒有效數
it does not catalyze
它不可以催化
So the reaction math speeds up
所以反應數理加快起來
so
這樣
Why when the pH value is lower
為什麼PH值越小的時候
Its crystallization period is smaller and more irregular
它晶期就是越小越不規則
Not necessarily not necessarily
沒有不一定不一定
not necessarily not necessarily
不一定不一定
I don't know you want to take a material not necessarily
我不知道你想拿一個材料不一定
what is not necessarily
什麼不一定
uncertain
不一定
Where is MX
MX在哪呢
that's not necessarily
那也不一定
That's what we want to control
那個也是我們要控制
Tell me about one of my articles
你再講我其中一篇入文的
i know what you're going to say
我知道你要講什麼
The nano hole
那個做奈米的孔洞
Dioxide series material
二氧化系材材
Then P is also empty
那P也是空之的
its big horns right
它的大角沒錯
yes
沒錯
But there are other variations
但是也有其他的變異
Or if you change the temperature and change the gas
或是如果去變了溫度和變氣
it's not the same
它不太一樣
I can't go into details about this.
這個細節我就沒辦法再多講
that's right
對啦 是沒錯
I probably know about your temperature problem
我大概知道你溫度問題的
maybe ask again
也許再問
behind this side
這邊後面
Beyond the level of this puzzling invention
在這個難迷發明的程度之外
a lot of this hygiene
很多這個衛生
All at the level of difficulty invented
都在難迷度發明的程度上
right
對
especially sick
尤其是病
it's a virus
它病毒呢
it seems
它好像
We call it this breeding
我們把它的這個繁殖
its energy
它的能源
out of its control
從它的控制
These problems are solved
這些問題都解決掉了
Then we are confused about the material
那我們難迷材料
Have you learned much about this?
在這方面有沒有學到多少
Learn from viruses
從病毒這一方面學習
virus it's
病毒它的
may say these things
可能說這些東西
its handed over to technology
它交給技術
it's not interested in itself
它自己並沒有興趣
Process Metabolism doesn't do these things
進程代謝沒有做這些事情
that's a good idea
這倒是一個好想法
Someday I will make a nano show
我哪天做個奈米戲去
to invade a cell
去侵占一個細胞
Let the cells do what I want
讓細胞幫我做我要的事情
maybe one day
也許有一天
But this requires a thorough understanding of life
但是這個要對生活有很徹底的了解
I think we're pretty good at this
我想我們在這方面本厲害
because you're here to be you
因為你們在這做你們
I mentioned this self-installation
就提到這個自主裝
Safe assembly
Safe assembly
What is our mechanism for Safe assembly?
我們對Safe assembly的機制到底是多少
simple
簡單的
If, for example, a surface mono layer
如果說譬如說一個表面的mono layer
Safe assembly
Safe assembly
like the outside world
像外界的時候
what does professor tao yutai do
陶宇台教授做什麼
that understands quite
那個了解相當
that is very restricted
那個很受限制
very limited
很受限
But if a three-dimensional structure
但是如果搭一個三維的結構
Then, if you take the level
然後還接層次的話
really know very little
真的知道很少
so many things are
所以很多事就是
just wear L
就是穿L
have to try more
就要多試
But there will be some hints and some conjectures
但會有一些hint會一些猜想
but no good theory
但是沒有很好的理論
you do those things
你去做那些事情
For mentioning this imitative word
因為提到這個仿神的話
generally speaking
一般說起來的話
is doing the most on the fly
是在飛行做得最多
also compare the best
也比較做得最好
that this
那這個
words in chemistry
化學方面的話
I feel like I did it late
我的感覺做得比較晚
How far are you doing now?
現在到底做得什麼程度
really
還真的是
It's a lot worse
是差很多很多
relatively late start
比較起步比較晚
Because this series of Nano moves it is very complicated
因為這個奈米的系列動它很複雜
It first has a joint structure
它第一有接成式的結構
Then it will be difficult for you to get out
那個你就很難走出來
The second is like schooling out something like this
第二像校出這種東西
it is very finely conditioned
它是很精細的調空
you don't look at it this center
你不要看它這個中心
the water pipe
那個裝水管
Everything around will be affected
旁邊每一件事情都會影響到的
It is difficult for us to imitate it completely
我們很難去完全模仿它
So the so-called bionics sometimes
所以所謂仿生有時候
That is to say, it is inspired to do this
就是說被它inspire來做這件事
behind that
那後面
that
那個
if the creature size
如果生物大小
Now some genetic engineering
那現在有些基因工程
Or use artificial hormones
或者是用人工那個荷爾蒙
actually allows fish to grow much faster or triple in size
事實上可以讓魚可以長得快很多或大量三倍
someone did it
這倒是有人做過
Like Shamon now with genetic engineering
像現在有基因工程的沙蒙
But it seems that I have just been allowed to work
不過好像剛上業被允許過
So how about being listed in that European country?
所以可以上市在那個歐洲國家怎麼樣
If you have a virus
那自己病毒的話
Many people now use genetically modified viruses
現在很多人用基因改造病毒
So this virus can help you make protein
所以這樣病毒可以幫你製造 protein
Or the tool of Ganggene delivery
或者剛基因delivery的工具什麼
This machine does a lot
這個機械做很多
But this is not completely artificial like yours.
不過這個不是像你們那種完全是人造做出來的
is this genetic modification
是這種基因改造
But here comes a problem
不過這裡到一個問題
Ask Professor Mao
像毛教授請問一下
I just mentioned that it's useful
剛剛提到說有用那種
The method of life is afraid of substances to replace this SOD
恍生的方法都恐物質來取代這種 SOD
So it can be used as a valid number
所以可以做有效數的作用
Now in terms of reproductive energy
那現在生殖能源方面
Many people use Sanway efficacious numbers
很多人是用Sanway 效數
The Sanway effect is very difficult to produce
那Sanway 效數非常難生產
then the wood is very hard
然後木材非常硬
very difficult to digest
非常難消化
Then you see, it means using your inexplicable technology
那你看就是說用你們這種恍生的技術
Replacing reproductive energy in the future
將來來取代生殖能源
to the possibility of digesting wood into energy
來把木材消化變成能源的可能性
How high is the new chance
新的機會有多高
The bionic one now
現在仿生的那個
efficacies to decompose that
效數去分解那個
made of fiber
纖維數做的
Can still make considerable progress
還可以有相當進展
But the hardest is the wooden number
但最難是木質數
that part of the wooden number
那個木質數那部分
really difficult
真的是很困難
let me see
我看一下
I can't imitate that effect
就模仿不出來那個效數
natural efficiency
天生效數
You can decompose that part of the wooden number
可以把那個木質數那部分分解
Do you know what I mean
你知道我的意思嗎
Fiber count is relatively easy is some
纖維數是比較容易就是一些
Lie together and cut that middle off
躺連在一起把那個中間切斷
But woody numbers are more complicated
但是木質數就複雜多了
a natural wood
一個天然的木材
it's very complicated inside
它裡面是非常複雜
we also
我們還
There is no way to deal with it all
還沒有辦法全部對付得下來
but in progress
但是在進展中
so
這樣
is there any problem
還有沒有有問題
or
或者
This because it does not specify
這個因為它不規定
just click
那按一下就是
press the green one
按那個綠的
good
好
Because I think bionic words
因為我覺得仿生的話
just like nature fucks
只是像大自然操系的
sometimes not very strong
有时候不是很强大
why
为什么呢
Because nature's requirements are different from our requirements
因为大自然的要求跟我们的要求
no the same
不一样
for example
比如说
In Taiwan we all like to make money first
在台湾我们都喜欢赚钱第一
the words of nature
这个大自然的话
I guess the idea of ​​making money isn't enough
我猜想是赚钱的观念还不够
it may be survival first
它可能是生存第一
So play today like a natural gymnastics
所以玩今天像大自然操系的话
I think sometimes it's not very strong
我觉得有时候不是很强大
Should I say yes
是不是应该说是
In addition to operating
除了操系以外
You are like these rises of nature
你像大自然的这些起似
inspiration
inspiration
yeah i just mentioned
对对 我刚刚有提到
In fact, many jobs are like this now
现在事实上很多工作是这样子的
otherwise
不然的话
We are now singing the high profile of this innovation
我们现在唱高调的这个创新
simply impossible
根本就不可能
Yes, from this body to
对 从这个身体到起似
in my speech today
在我今天的演讲里面
I did not put the Bio-Memetic
我没有把Bio-Memetic
Let me distinguish between these two Inspires
就把我Inspire这两支去做区分
maybe i should make it next time
也许我下次应该把它做
better distinction
比较好的区分
In fact many jobs are Bio-Inspired
事实上很多工作是Bio-Inspire
no
不是
imitated but by his natural
模仿而是被他的大自然的
to spark your imagination
去激发你的想象
Many jobs are of the form
很多工作是属于这样的形式
i think this is
我想这个是
He should be distinguished
应该都给他区分出来的
Because I heard stuff stuff
因为我听说材料的玩意
materials of nature
大自然的材料
especially hard materials
尤其比较硬的材料
it has few basic elements
它的基本元素很少
It is all structured
它都是structured
it is structured
它是structured
the technology of our characters
那我们人物的技术
It's just a little bit different
好像刚好有点不太一样
on the contrary
相反
We say that the basic elements are many
我们说基本元素很多
The middle of the result
结果中间的这个
The so-called structured
所谓structured
not too much
不太多
But workers we seem
但是工人我们好像
less natural materials
不如大自然的材料
Its optimization is very good
它的optimation做得非常好
Yes, this understanding is very
是 这个理解是有很
Nature has dozens of years
大自然有几十一年的时间
we don't have that long
我们没有那么长时间
they have thirty one years
他们有三十一年的时间
progress slowly
慢慢去进步
to evolve him
去演化他
right
对
we don't have that long
我们没有那么长时间
so
所以
Especially since I just said a lot
尤其我刚刚讲了很多
is playing now
是现在在演
Existing theme
就有的題材
so we are still learning
所以我們還在學
we are really far behind
我們真的差很多
talk to nature
跟大自然的話
still a lot worse
還是差很多很多
So we have to learn from nature
所以我們要向大自然學習
ok thanks Kohman
好 謝謝Kohman
is there any problem
還有沒有什麼問題
well, talk about nothing
好 講到沒有的話
we'll be a drummer later
我們待會兒是鼓場
Thank you Professor Nakahara
謝謝某中原教授的
Jin Xia's speech
金俠的演講
Thank you for your participation
謝謝大家的參與
Thanks
謝謝